store.morganclaypool.com
ABOUT SYNTHESIS
This volume is a printed version of a work that appears in the 
Synthesis Digital Library of 
Engineering and Computer Science
.  Synthesis Lectures provide concise original presentations 
of important research and development topics, published quickly in digital and print formats. 
For more information, visit our website: http://store.morganclaypool.com
Biologically Inspired Design 
A Primer
Torben A. Lenau
, 
Danmarks Tekniske Universitet
Akhlesh Lakhtakia
, 
The Pennsylvania State University
 
As the existence of all life forms on our planet is currently in grave danger from the climate emergency 
caused by 
Homo sapiens
, the words “sustainability” and “eco-responsibility” have entered the daily-use 
vocabularies of scientists, engineers, economists, business managers, industrialists, capitalists, and policy 
makers. Normal activities undertaken for the design of products and systems in industrialisms must 
be revamped. As the bioworld is a great resource for eco-responsible design activities, an overview of 
biologically inspired design is presented in this book in simple terms for anyone with even high-school 
education.
 
Beginning with an introduction to the process of design in industry, the book presents the bioworld 
as a design resource along with the rationale for biologically inspired design. Problem-driven and 
solution-driven approaches for biologically inspired design are described next. The last chapter is 
focused on biologically inspired design for environment.
BIOLOGICALLY INSPIRED DESIGN: A PRIMER
LENAU • LAKHTAKIA
MORGAN & CLAYPOOL
 Biologically Inspired Design
A Primer
  Synthesis Lectures on
Engineering, Science, and
Technology
Each book in the series is written by a well known expert in the ﬁeld. Most titles cover subjects
such as professional development, education, and study skills, as well as basic introductory
undergraduate material and other topics appropriate for a broader and less technical audience.
In addition, the series includes several titles written on very speciﬁc topics not covered
elsewhere in the Synthesis Digital Library.
Biologically Inspired Design: A Primer
Torben A. Lenau and Akhlesh Lakhtakia
2021
Engineering Design: An Organic Approach to Solving Complex Problems in the Modern
World
George D. Catalano and Karen C. Catalano
2020
Integrated Process Design and Operational Optimization via Multiparametric
Programming
Baris Burnak, Nikolaos A. Diangelakis, and Efstratios N. Pistikopoulos
2020
The Art of Teaching Physics with Ancient Chinese Science and Technology
Matt Marone
2020
Scientiﬁc Analysis of Cultural Heritage Objects
Michael Wiescher and Khachatur Manukyan
2020
Case Studies in Forensic Physics
Gregory A. DiLisi and Richard A. Rarick
2020
 iv
An Introduction to Numerical Methods for the Physical Sciences
Colm T. Whelan
2020
Nanotechnology Past and Present
Deb Newberry
2020
Introduction to Engineering Research
Wendy C. Crone
2020
Theory of Electromagnetic Beams
John Lekner
2020
The Search for the Absolute: How Magic Became Science
Jeﬀrey H. Williams
2020
The Big Picture: The Universe in Five S.T.E.P.S.
John Beaver
2020
Relativistic Classical Mechanics and Electrodynamics
Martin Land and Lawrence P. Horwitz
2019
Generating Functions in Engineering and the Applied Sciences
Rajan Chattamvelli and Ramalingam Shanmugam
2019
Transformative Teaching: A Collection of Stories of Engineering Faculty’s Pedagogical
Journeys
Nadia Kellam, Brooke Coley, and Audrey Boklage
2019
Ancient Hindu Science: Its Transmission and Impact on World Cultures
Alok Kumar
2019
Value Rational Engineering
Shuichi Fukuda
2018
 v
Strategic Cost Fundamentals: for Designers, Engineers, Technologists, Estimators,
Project Managers, and Financial Analysts
Robert C. Creese
2018
Concise Introduction to Cement Chemistry and Manufacturing
Tadele Assefa Aragaw
2018
Data Mining and Market Intelligence: Implications for Decision Making
Mustapha Akinkunmi
2018
Empowering Professional Teaching in Engineering: Sustaining the Scholarship of
Teaching
John Heywood
2018
The Human Side of Engineering
John Heywood
2017
Geometric Programming for Design Equation Development and Cost/Proﬁt
Optimization (with illustrative case study problems and solutions), Third Edition
Robert C. Creese
2016
Engineering Principles in Everyday Life for Non-Engineers
Saeed Benjamin Niku
2016
A, B, See... in 3D: A Workbook to Improve 3-D Visualization Skills
Dan G. Dimitriu
2015
The Captains of Energy: Systems Dynamics from an Energy Perspective
Vincent C. Prantil and Timothy Decker
2015
Lying by Approximation: The Truth about Finite Element Analysis
Vincent C. Prantil, Christopher Papadopoulos, and Paul D. Gessler
2013
Simpliﬁed Models for Assessing Heat and Mass Transfer in Evaporative Towers
Alessandra De Angelis, Onorio Saro, Giulio Lorenzini, Stefano D’Elia, and Marco Medici
2013
 vi
The Engineering Design Challenge: A Creative Process
Charles W. Dolan
2013
The Making of Green Engineers: Sustainable Development and the Hybrid Imagination
Andrew Jamison
2013
Crafting Your Research Future: A Guide to Successful Master’s and Ph.D. Degrees in
Science & Engineering
Charles X. Ling and Qiang Yang
2012
Fundamentals of Engineering Economics and Decision Analysis
David L. Whitman and Ronald E. Terry
2012
A Little Book on Teaching: A Beginner’s Guide for Educators of Engineering and
Applied Science
Steven F. Barrett
2012
Engineering Thermodynamics and 21st Century Energy Problems: A Textbook
Companion for Student Engagement
Donna Riley
2011
MATLAB for Engineering and the Life Sciences
Joseph V. Tranquillo
2011
Systems Engineering: Building Successful Systems
Howard Eisner
2011
Fin Shape Thermal Optimization Using Bejan’s Constructal Theory
Giulio Lorenzini, Simone Moretti, and Alessandra Conti
2011
Geometric Programming for Design and Cost Optimization (with illustrative case study
problems and solutions), Second Edition
Robert C. Creese
2010
Survive and Thrive: A Guide for Untenured Faculty
Wendy C. Crone
2010
 vii
Geometric Programming for Design and Cost Optimization (with Illustrative Case Study
Problems and Solutions)
Robert C. Creese
2009
Style and Ethics of Communication in Science and Engineering
Jay D. Humphrey and Jeﬀrey W. Holmes
2008
Introduction to Engineering: A Starter’s Guide with Hands-On Analog Multimedia
Explorations
Lina J. Karam and Naji Mounsef
2008
Introduction to Engineering: A Starter’s Guide with Hands-On Digital Multimedia and
Robotics Explorations
Lina J. Karam and Naji Mounsef
2008
CAD/CAM of Sculptured Surfaces on Multi-Axis NC Machine: The DG/K-Based
Approach
Stephen P. Radzevich
2008
Tensor Properties of Solids, Part Two: Transport Properties of Solids
Richard F. Tinder
2007
Tensor Properties of Solids, Part One: Equilibrium Tensor Properties of Solids
Richard F. Tinder
2007
Essentials of Applied Mathematics for Scientists and Engineers
Robert G. Watts
2007
Project Management for Engineering Design
Charles Lessard and Joseph Lessard
2007
Relativistic Flight Mechanics and Space Travel
Richard F. Tinder
2006
 Copyright © 2021 by Morgan & Claypool
All rights reserved. No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in
any form or by any means—electronic, mechanical, photocopy, recording, or any other except for brief quotations
in printed reviews, without the prior permission of the publisher.
Biologically Inspired Design: A Primer
Torben A. Lenau and Akhlesh Lakhtakia
www.morganclaypool.com
ISBN: 9781636390475
paperback
ISBN: 9781636390482
ebook
ISBN: 9781636390499
hardcover
DOI 10.2200/S01064ED1V01Y202012EST014
A Publication in the Morgan & Claypool Publishers series
SYNTHESIS LECTURES ON ENGINEERING, SCIENCE, AND TECHNOLOGY
Lecture #14
Series ISSN
Print 2690-0300
Electronic 2690-0327
 Biologically Inspired Design
A Primer
Torben A. Lenau
Danmarks Tekniske Universitet
Akhlesh Lakhtakia
The Pennsylvania State University
SYNTHESIS LECTURES ON ENGINEERING, SCIENCE, AND
TECHNOLOGY #14
C
M
&
cLaypool publishers
Morgan
&
 ABSTRACT
As the existence of all life forms on our planet is currently in grave danger from the climate emer-
gency caused by
Homo sapiens
, the words “sustainability” and “eco-responsibility” have entered
the daily-use vocabularies of scientists, engineers, economists, business managers, industrialists,
capitalists, and policy makers. Normal activities undertaken for the design of products and sys-
tems in industrialisms must be revamped. As the bioworld is a great resource for eco-responsible
design activities, an overview of biologically inspired design is presented in this book in simple
terms for anyone with even high-school education.
Beginning with an introduction to the process of design in industry, the book presents the
bioworld as a design resource along with the rationale for biologically inspired design. Problem-
driven and solution-driven approaches for biologically inspired design are described next. The
last chapter is focused on biologically inspired design for environment.
KEYWORDS
bioinspiration, biomimicry, biomimetics, bioreplication, bionik, bionics, nature-
inspired design, circular economy, contraindicated performance, design for envi-
ronment, eco-eﬃciency, engineered biomimicry, multifunctionality, sustainability
 xi
Dedicated to sustainable societies
  xiii
Contents
Preface
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
xvii
Acknowledgments
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
xix
1
Deﬁnitions
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
1
1.1
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4
2
What is Design?
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
5
2.1
Introduction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5
2.2
Design Thinking . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6
2.3
The Design Object . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6
2.4
Design Process . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 7
2.4.1
Task Clariﬁcation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 11
2.4.2
Function Analysis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 13
2.4.3
Design Brief and Product Speciﬁcation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
2.4.4
Conceptual Design . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 15
2.4.5
Concept Evaluation . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17
2.4.6
Toward Detailed Design . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 17
2.5
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 18
3
Engineered Biomimicry: Solutions from the Bioworld
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
21
3.1
The Case for Engineered Biomimicry . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 21
3.2
Engineered Biomimicry . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 22
3.2.1
Bioinspiration . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 23
3.2.2
Biomimetics . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 23
3.2.3
Bioreplication . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24
3.3
Examples of Engineered Biomimicry . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24
3.3.1
Bioinspired Computational Techniques . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24
3.3.2
Biomimetic Production of Human Insulin . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 26
3.3.3
Bioreplicated Visual Decoys of Insects. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 29
3.4
Design Teams for Bioworld Solutions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 32
3.5
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 33
 xiv
4
Rationale for Biologically Inspired Design
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
37
4.1
Energy Eﬃciency . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 37
4.2
Circular Economy of Materials . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 38
4.3
Multifunctionality . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 39
4.4
Multicontrollability . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40
4.5
Suboptimality . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 40
4.6
Contraindicated Performance . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 41
4.7
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 43
5
Problem-Driven Biologically Inspired Design
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
47
5.1
Introduction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 47
5.2
Phases of Problem-Driven BID. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 48
5.2.1
First Phase: Problem Analysis . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 49
5.2.2
Second Phase: Search . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 54
5.2.3
Third Phase: Understand . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 55
5.2.4
Fourth Phase: Transfer . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 56
5.2.5
Fifth Phase: Design . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 57
5.3
Engineers and Biologists . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 58
5.4
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 59
6
Solution-Driven Biologically Inspired Design
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
61
6.1
Introduction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 61
6.2
Examples of Solution-Driven BID . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 62
6.2.1
Mycelium Bio-Composites . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 62
6.2.2
Bombardier-Beetle Spray . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 63
6.2.3
Tubercles for Flow Control . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 65
6.2.4
Abalone-Shell Armor . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 66
6.3
Steps for Solution-Driven BID . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 68
6.3.1
Application Search . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 68
6.3.2
Eight-Step Procedure . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 70
6.4
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 74
7
Biologically Inspired Design for the Environment
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
77
7.1
Sustainability and the Environment . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 77
7.2
Matter of Scale . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 79
7.3
Sustainable Practices from Nature . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 80
 xv
7.4
Circular Economy of Materials . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 81
7.5
Mutually Beneﬁcial Coexistence . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 82
7.6
Energy Eﬃciency . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 83
7.7
Design Approaches . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 84
7.7.1
Environmental Guidelines . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 84
7.7.2
Circular Design . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 85
7.7.3
Impact Assessment . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 87
7.8
Grafting “Biologically Inspired Design” onto “Design for Environment” . . . . 87
7.9
References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 89
Authors’ Biographies
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
95
  xvii
Preface
This primer on biologically inspired design (BID) was initiated during a sabbatical semester
spent by Akhlesh Lakhtakia at Danmarks Tekniske Universitet (DTU) during the second half of
2019, at the invitation of Torben A. Lenau. The close collaboration between both of us resulted
not only in the descriptions of BID approaches and the case stories required to make the reading
of this book interesting to undergraduate students enrolled for BID courses, but it also made
a collaboration possible with Daniela C. A. Pigosso and Tim C. McAloone for grafting BID
onto
design for environment
. The combination of the two design foci makes it possible to tap into
the enormous knowledge bank that the bioworld represents and apply well-proven solutions in
the quest to secure sustainable societies and ecosystems on our planet.
Torben A. Lenau started in 2009 to teach BID to engineering students at DTU. More
than 400 students have marched through the course since then. The course is focused on the
problem-driven approach to BID illustrated by around a hundred case studies.
The solution-driven approach to BID complements the problem-driven approach. Both
are treated in two chapters in this book. They are described in suﬃcient detail to allow practi-
tioners as well as students to follow and apply the approaches to their own BID activities. As
this book explains BID in simple terms for anyone with even high-school education, we hope
that not only engineering and design students but also members of the general public interested
in sustainability will proﬁt from the time they will spend on reading this primer on BID.
Torben A. Lenau and Akhlesh Lakhtakia
January 2021
  xix
Acknowledgments
Torben A. Lenau thanks the many students of Danmarks Tekniske Universitet (DTU) who
took his course 41084 Biologically Inspired Design over the years for providing the empirical
experience and contextual setting that stimulated the development of methodological support
tools. He is also highly grateful for insightful discussions with and support from his wife Ingrid.
Akhlesh Lakhtakia is grateful to the Trustees of The Pennsylvania State University for a
sabbatical leave of absence, the Otto Mønsted Foundation for partial ﬁnancial support, and the
Department of Mechanical Engineering, DTU for gracious hospitality in Fall 2019 semester.
He also thanks Mercedes for wonderful spousal support during that period.
Both of us are grateful to Daniela C. A. Pigosso and Tim C. McAloone for discussions
on grafting
biologically inspired design
onto
design for environment
. We thank Patrick D. McAtee
for several suggestions as well as for alerting us to several errors in a draft manuscript, and the
staﬀ of Morgan & Claypool for splendid cooperation in producing this book.
Torben A. Lenau and Akhlesh Lakhtakia
January 2021
  1
C H A P T E R
1
Deﬁnitions
“Begin at the beginning,” the King said, very gravely,
“and go on till you come to the end: then stop.”
Lewis Carroll,
Alice in Wonderland
(1865)
First things ﬁrst, we must begin with deﬁnitions. This is all the more necessary for a rapidly
emerging area such as engineered biomimicry, which encompasses both basic research on
outcomes and mechanisms of diverse phenomena displayed by living organisms and the appli-
cation of fundamental principles uncovered by that basic research to devise useful processes and
products [ ]. Engineered biomimicry can thrive in an industrialism, which is a society replete
1
with manufacturing industries for mass production of a diverse array of products.
Biomimicry lies within the ambit of engineered biomimicry. Although the two terms
are often used as synonyms of each other, biomimicry additionally incorporates the attributes of
sustainability evinced by the bioworld. Sustainability is deﬁned as the maintenance of natural
resources for ecological balance; hence, present-day needs are satisﬁed without endangering the
ability of future generations to do the same [ ]. Sustainability mandates the formation of those
2
industrial ecosystems that are founded on the principles of circular economy. The main out-
puts, byproducts, and wastes of every segment of a circular economy become inputs to one or
more of the other segments of that economy, thereby minimizing the overall resource inputs to
the circular economy [ ]. The inter-relationships of engineered biomimicry, biomimicry, sus-
3
tainability, and industrialism are schematically depicted in Fig.
1.1
.
Design and manufacture are the two main engineering activities in any industry. Accord-
ingly, engineered biomimicry encompasses both biologically inspired design and manufacture,
as depicted in Fig.
1.2
. The scope of biologically inspired design is the formulation of de-
sign strategies to reproduce desirable outcomes, mechanisms, and structures from the bioworld.
A manufacturing action may or may not be provenanced in the bioworld.
The history of
Homo sapiens
is marked by numerous approaches to the solution of engineer-
ing problems based on solutions from the bioworld. These approaches of engineered biomimicry
can be classiﬁed as bioinspiration, biomimetics, and bioreplication, as shown also in Fig.
1.2
.
The goal in bioinspiration is to reproduce a biological outcome without reproducing the
underlying physical mechanism(s) and the biological structure(s). As an example, powered ﬂying
machines were inspired by birds in self-powered ﬂight. But airplanes do not ﬂap their wings like
birds, and the tails of birds are horizontal unlike the vertical tails of aeroplanes. Rotorcraft do
 2
1. DEFINITIONS
Sustainable
actions
Biomimicry
Engineered
biomimicry
Industrialism
(mass production)
Figure 1.1:
Engineered biomimicry and biomimicry within the contexts of sustainable actions
and mass production.
Engineered biomimicry
Biomimetics
Bioinspiration
Biologically
inspired
design
Production
Bioreplication
Figure 1.2:
Conceptual anatomy of engineered biomimicry.
 1. DEFINITIONS
3
not ﬂy like birds either. But these engineered structures do reproduce the natural outcome of
moving from one location to another without being in physical contact with the ground.
Biomimetics is the reproduction of a physical mechanism responsible for a speciﬁc func-
tionality exhibited by a biological structure. The classic example of biomimetics is Velcro™ com-
prising dense assemblies of hooks and loops, the former emulating the hooked barbs on a bur-
dock seed and the latter the fur of a furry animal. When a furry animal brushes against a burdock
seed, the hooks get fastened to the fur. The International Standards Origanization (ISO) has
formulated a set of criteria for whether a product can be considered as biomimetic [ ]. The crite-
4
ria relate to the biomimetic design process which was applied to develop the product and require
that
(i) a function analysis has been performed on an available biological system,
(ii) the essential mechanisms in that biological system have been abstracted into a model, and
(iii) the model has been transferred and applied to design the product.
Bioreplication is the direct replication of a structure found in a biological organism
in order to reproduce one or more functionalities exhibited by the biological structure copied.
Decoys created by nanoscale replication of the actual elytra of a female emerald ash borer for the
purpose of sexually attracting male emerald ash borers provide an example of bioreplication [ ].
5
The term biomaterial refers to either a material harvested from a biological organism
to be used for the same purpose as in the organism or an artiﬁcial material used for a biological
purpose. In the latter case, the term biocompatible material is also used. Bovine milk is a
biomaterial of the ﬁrst kind, being produced in the bioworld as a nutrient for calves and also
used by humans as food. Prostheses for human hips and knees are made of biomaterials of the
second kind.
Biomanufacturing uses a biological process to produce a synthetic product. Thus, syn-
thetic insulin is produced by inserting the human insulin genes in open loops of bacterial DNA to
close the latter, the closed loops are inserted in bacteria which multiply rapidly in a fermentation
chamber, the insulin then being harvested from the bacteria being produced in that chamber.
Escherichia coli
and
Saccharomyces cerevisiae
are commonly used species of bacteria, but yeast, a
fungus, often replaces the bacteria in this biomanufacturing process [ ]. A speciﬁc biomanufac-
6
turing process has at least one component that is either biomimetic or bioreplicatory.
A structure is multifunctional if it can perform two or more distinct functions that
are not highly related to each other [ ]. An example of multifunctionality is displayed in the
7
bioworld by skin, which contains the organism, deﬁnes its shape and size, hosts a variety of sen-
sors, and may be used to camouﬂage as well as to advertise. The fuselage of an aircraft functions
both as a thermal isolator and an acoustic isolator. The well-known Swiss Army™ knife is a
multifunctional tool.
The output of a multicontrollable structure can be controlled independently by more
than one mechanisms [ ]. As natural examples: the same sound can be uttered using two or three
8
 4
1. DEFINITIONS
diﬀerent conﬁgurations of the tongue and the buccal cavity, and multiple modes of locomotion
can be used by an organism to propel itself from one location to another.
1.1
REFERENCES
[1] A. Lakhtakia and R. J. Martín-Palma (Eds.),
Engineered Biomimicry
, Elsevier, Waltham,
MA, 2013.
DOI: 10.1016/c2011-0-06814-x 1
.
[2] M. Mulligan,
An Introduction to Sustainability: Environmental, Social and Personal Perspec-
tives
, 2nd ed., Routledge, Abingdon, Oxford, UK, 2018.
DOI: 10.4324/978131588852
.
1
[3] W. R. Stahel,
Circular Economy: A User’s Guide
, Routledge, Abingdon, Oxford, UK, 2019.
1
[4] ISO 18458:2015,
Biomimetics—Terminology, Concepts and Methodology
, International
Standards Organization, Geneva, Switzerland, 2015.
https://www.iso.org/standard/
62500.html DOI: 10.3403/30274979 3
.
[5] M. J. Domingue, A. Lakhtakia, D. P. Pulsifer, L. P. Hall, J. V. Badding, J. L. Bischof, R. J.
Martín-Palma, Z. Imrei, G. Janik, V. C. Mastro, M. Hazen, and T. C. Baker, Bioreplicated
visual features of nanofabricated buprestid beetle decoys evoke stereotypical male mating
ﬂights,
Proceedings of U.S. National Academy of Sciences
, 111:14106–14111, 2014.
DOI:
10.1073/pnas.1412810111 3
.
[6] N. A. Baeshen, M. N. Baeshen, A. Sheikh, R. S. Bora, M. M. M. Ahmed, H. A. I.
Ramadan, K. S. Saini, and E. M. Redwan, Cell factories for insulin production,
Microbial
Cell Factories
, 13:141, 2014.
DOI: 10.1186/s12934-014-0141-0 3
.
[7] A. Lakhtakia, From bioinspired multifunctionality to mimumes,
Bioinspired, Biomimetic
and Nanobiomaterials
, 4:168–173, 2015.
DOI: 10.1117/12.2258683 3
.
[8] A. Lakhtakia, D. E. Wolfe, M. W. Horn, J. Mazurowski, A. Burger, and P. P. Banerjee,
Bioinspired multicontrollable metasurfaces and metamaterials for terahertz applications,
Proceedings of SPIE
, 10162:101620V, 2017.
DOI: 10.1117/12.2258683 3
.
 5
C H A P T E R
2
What is Design?
It is not enough that we build products that function, that are
understandable and usable, we also need to build products
that bring joy and excitement, pleasure and fun,
and, yes, beauty to people’s lives.
Donald A. Norman (2004)
1
2.1
INTRODUCTION
Design has been around for as long as humans have created things. Design and making were not
separate until the rise of the age of factories, since the craft-person designed the product while
making it [ ]. For example, a potter would make a pot by working with clay without ﬁrst making
1
drawings. This was possible as long as the product was simple and the production process was
implemented close to the people using the product. However, modern products are usually very
complicated and are often produced at locations far away from their users’.
This development engendered the need for more formalized design activity whereby
designers analyze user needs and create documentation so that the product can be later man-
ufactured by others elsewhere. The documentation must be detailed and accurate in specifying
form, materials, dimensions, and other variable parameters.
A design activity need not be formal and often it is not; however, it must be eﬀective.
Methods and tools are therefore developed to improve the likelihood of matching user needs to
a good new product whose production is cost eﬀective and which can be expediently disposed
oﬀ after use. In writing this book, we expect that biologically inspired design will help
designers in identifying good solution principles and even get detailed inputs for how to realize
the product structure and functionality.
Apart from ﬁnding solutions to functional needs, design is also about product appearance
and the messages the product sends. This is clearly obvious for clothing and automobiles, because
high premiums are paid for exclusive looks. Many automobiles are designed to communicate the
impression of speed and power. This is done by borrowing design features from animals with
those characteristics. For example, automobile headlights are designed to remind the bystander
of the eyes of tigers or lions. Cute animals inspire children’s toys and sports equipment draw
1
D.A. Norman, Introduction to this special section on beauty, goodness, and usability,
Human-Computer Interaction
,
19:311–318, 2004.
 6
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
on visual inspiration from agile animals such as cheetahs. Biological inspiration for product
appearance is a huge area, but this book is focused on how to utilize functional solutions found
in the bioworld.
2.2
DESIGN THINKING
The concept of design thinking is often invoked to distinguish design activities from scientiﬁc
problem solving wherein underlying principles are uncovered systematically to ﬁnd optimal so-
lutions. In contrast, design thinking requires multiple explorations to identify a range of possible
solutions from which a satisfactory one is identiﬁed.
The major diﬀerence in the thought processes of scientists and designers was exposed in
an experiment more than four decades ago [ ]. A group of ﬁfth-year students from architecture
2
and a similar group from science were asked to arrange building blocks with colored sides with
the goal of maximizing the number of sides of a speciﬁc color. The results suggested that science
students selected blocks in order to discover the structure of the problem, whereas architecture
students generated sequences of blocks until a combination proved acceptable.
Design thinking is claimed to be suitable for solving an ill-posed problem by sketching
several possible solutions to understand it from diﬀerent viewpoints [ , ]. It calls for a mindset,
1 3
as can be seen from analyzing the preferred ways of working of many designers. The mindset
includes a strong user focus and the will to understand the core of the problem by generating a
large space of many solutions. Several of these solutions will be visualized and even prototyped
before a solution is ﬁnally selected for production.
2.3
THE DESIGN OBJECT
From a ﬁrst look, it seems obvious that the product is the design object. However, further
analysis clariﬁes that the design object also includes other elements such as single components
or parts within the product; the overall system within which the product functions; and the
non-material services associated with its merchandizing, use, and eventual disposal.
When designing, the goal is to produce a thing to satisfy a need. This thing can be a phys-
ical product such as a toothbrush or an automobile, or it can be a service such as linen laundry
in a hotel. Clearly, the complexity of the design process varies with the type of the product or
service to be designed. The delimitation of the design object is therefore important. The tooth-
brush is a single component even though it is permanently assembled from a plastic handle
and several clumps of brushing hairs. On the other hand, an automobile is a larger collection
of single components that are conﬁgured in subsystems which together are assembled into the
complete product: the automobile. However, an automobile is part of a larger system includ-
ing gas stations, repair shops, roads, and parking spots, which together are necessary to provide
the transportation functionality to the user. Furthermore, the product is part of a larger con-
text which has a major impact on how the product is designed. Automobiles of diﬀerent types
 2.4. DESIGN PROCESS
7
are made to satisfy needs in diverse contexts, as exempliﬁed by minivans to transport families
with children, mobile homes for leisure activities, mobile workshops for mechanics, and taxis to
transport visitors with luggage.
The bioworld shows similar features. Organisms of many diﬀerent types co-exist in a
mutualistic relationship system that is the prerequisite for the existence of a single organism in
that system. In other words, the system comprises its constituent organisms as subunits with
speciﬁc roles and interfaces to the rest of the organisms. Removal of organisms of a certain
type from the system can seriously alter, and even demolish, the latter. In the same way, each
organism consists of several organs and other subunits with speciﬁc roles and interfaces to the
rest of the organism. When seeking inspiration from the bioworld, it is therefore beneﬁcial to
also look at the larger system that the organism is part of.
One major diﬀerence between the bioworld and design activity must be noted. A new
feature in an organism arises in the bioworld as a result of random modiﬁcations of parental
DNA. Most of these mutations are either inconsequential or harmful, but a certain mutation
may confer reproductive success in the prevailing environment. That mutation becomes more
prevalent in succeeding generations. A new species emerges in consequence of a succession of
numerous mutations, which makes sudden innovation impossible in the bioworld [ ], the oc-
4
currence of elevated emergence rates of new species in the fossil record [ , ] notwithstanding.
5 6
For example, a marine species cannot evolve into an avian one through just one mutation. In
contrast, although design activity is greatly limited by the availability of materials, tools, and
expertise, disruptive innovation is possible by the interjection of a radically new concept. As
an example, the emergence of the smartphones in 1992 from the predecessor telephones was
a single-step achievement inasmuch as a smartphone possesses a touch screen, can email, store
notes, keep a calender, and run diverse apps and widgets that would become widespread within
a decade. Furthermore, smartphones began to provide very convenient access to the internet,
thereby taking away a market segment from laptop manufacturers [ ].
7
2.4
DESIGN PROCESS
While there is a general agreement that every design process starts with a user need and is
expected to end with a solution, there are many models for structuring, organizing, and docu-
menting design processes. The Pahl–Beitz model shown in Fig.
2.1
encompasses the following
stages in sequence: task clariﬁcation, development of concepts (i.e., principal solutions), pre-
liminary layout, deﬁnitive layout, and documentation [ ]. Even though the model is sequential,
8
it is recognized that many iterative loops will be made if the result of an activity is unsatisfactory.
The Cross model shown in Fig.
2.2
is organized so the diﬀerent stages in a design activity
form a circle [ ]. The model makes it more apparent that design is an iterative activity wherein
1
all decisions are revisited several times before a good ﬁnal solution is found. Both the Pahl–Beitz
model and the Cross model require a function analysis to be undertaken before the design is
speciﬁed. In the Pahl–Beitz model, function analysis takes place during concept development,
 8
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
Analyze the market and company situation
Find and select product ideas
Formulate product proposal
Clarify the task
Elaborate requirement list
Task
Market, company, economy
Information
Upgrade and improve
Planning and
clarifying the task
Conceptual design
Embodiment design
Detail design
Requirements list
(design speciﬁcation)
Concept
(principal solution)
Preliminary layout
Deﬁnitive layout
Product documentation
Solution
Plan and
clarify
the task:
Develop the
principal
solution:
Develop the
construction
solution:
Deﬁne the
construction
structure:
Prepare
production
and operating
documents:
Identify essential problems
Establish function structures
Search for working principles and working structures
Combine and ﬁrm up into concept variants
Evaluate against technical and economic criteria
Preliminary form design, material selection, and
   calculation
Select best preliminary layouts
Reﬁne and improve layouts
Evaluate against technical and economic criteria
Eliminate weak spots
Check for errors, disturbing inﬂuences, and
   minimum costs
Prepare the preliminary parts list and production
   and assembly documents
Elaborate detail drawings and parts list
Complete production, assembly, transport, and
   operating instructions
Check all documents
Figure 2.1:
The Pahl–Beitz model of systematic design activity [ ].
8
 2.4. DESIGN PROCESS
9
Requirements
Characteristics
Objectives
Opportunities
Stage ﬂow
direction
Alternatives
Evaluation
Functions
Improvement
Overall
problem
Overall
solution
Sub-
problem
Sub-
solutions
Figure 2.2:
The Cross model of systematic design activity [ ].
1
with problem identiﬁcation linked to the search for working principles. In the Cross model,
function analysis is used to analyze the overall design problem and break it into subproblems.
A diﬀerence between the two models is the explicit focus on alternatives in the Cross model.
Generating alternative solutions is an important way to ﬁgure out how the design problem is
best solved. The Pahl–Beitz model, of course, recognizes this matter but the linear format of the
model does not invite consideration of alternatives.
Illustrated in Fig.
2.3
, the Tjalve model is a sequential model of design activity contain-
ing iterative loops [ ]. With more emphasis on concept development than in the previous two
9
models, the Tjalve model encompasses the stages of problem analysis; identiﬁcation of main
functions; identiﬁcation of sub-functions and means; formulation of the basic structure of the
product; quantiﬁcation of the product structure; delimitation of materials, dimensions, and sur-
faces; and the overall form of the product. Whereas the Pahl–Beitz and Cross models are well
suited for managing and coordinating design processes, the Tjalve model aims at guiding the
designer in creative activities.
Indeed, the Tjalve model deﬁnes the product in terms of ﬁve basic attributes. These are
the structure of the product with its constituent elements and relations, along with the form,
material, dimensions, and surface of each element. Thus, this model is a journey from an abstract
description of the product using functions toward gradually more and more concrete descriptions
of the overall structure and the constituent elements. Solutions are identiﬁed for each function,
the arrangement of the solutions being called the basic structure. The basic structure is typically
described using symbolic graphs rather than drawings illustrating the appearance of the prod-
uct. The quantiﬁed structure developed thereafter contains dimensions as well as the physical
arrangement of the constituent elements.
 10
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
Main
functions
C
r
i
t
e
r
i
a
Problem
analysis
Sub-functions
and means
Basic
structure
Quantiﬁed
structure
Total form
Form of
the elements
Material
Dimension
Surface
Figure 2.3:
The Tjalve model of systematic design activity [ ].
9
The Tjalve model emphasizes the need for alternatives and gives detailed inspiration for
how to systematically explore diﬀerent basic structures that will satisfy the functional require-
ments. Several alternatives are also generated for the quantiﬁed structure, wherein the con-
stituent elements can be conﬁgured diﬀerently in relation to each other. A useful division be-
tween the total form of the product and the forms of the constituent elements allows for the
search for partial solutions for single functions which later are combined into the total solution.
Finally, the integrated-product-development model shown in Fig.
2.4
emphasizes that
product design is not done in isolation but in parallel and close collaboration with market- and
production-oriented activities [
10
]. While designers consider the type of product to design, the
marketing team investigates competing products and determines whether there is room for a new
 2.4. DESIGN PROCESS
11
Determining
the basic
need
Determining
the type of
product
Consideration
of product
type
User
investigation
Product
principle
design
Determining
type of
production
Market
investigation
Product
design
phase
Product
principle
phase
Investigation
of need
phase
Recognition
of need
phase
Production
preparation
phase
Execution
phase
Preliminary
product
design
Determining
production
principles
Preparation
for sales
Modiﬁcation
for
manufacture
Preparation
for
production
Sales
Product
adaptation
Production
5
4
3
2
1
0
!e
Need
* INTEGRATED PRODUCT DEVELOPMENT
Figure 2.4:
The integrated-product-development model of systematic design activity [ ].
10
product in the market, and the production team investigates diverse options for manufacturing
the product.
2.4.1
TASK CLARIFICATION
A design process can be initiated by many diﬀerent triggers [
11
]. A common trigger is the user
need for a good solution, inadequate and barely adequate solutions being unsatisfactory. Another
trigger is the introduction of a new technology, as exempliﬁed by the emergence of social media
triggered by the introduction of smartphones. Yet another trigger is the economic aﬀordability
of a technology. For instance, the low prices of eﬃcient batteries have caused a boom in the use
of electrical scooters and bicycles.
Once a user need has been identiﬁed, the design process has to be articulated. This is most
often done either verbally or in writing, but a powerful alternative way is to provide diagrams. In
order not to restrict the design process, the focus should be on highlighting the need but not on
describing how it has been solved previously. This can be done by describing the consequences
of satisfying the need through before/after pictures like the ones commonly used in advertise-
ments for diet pills and other weight-reduction regimen. By visualizing the need, the designer
avoids ﬁxation on existing solutions and becomes receptive to innovative solutions. Being readily
understood, graphics are also eﬀective in communicating with stakeholders.
Many design processes actually involve re-design of existing products. Re-design can be
initiated either for improved functionality or to alleviate shortcomings experienced in existing
products. A detailed analysis of how users behave in the situations calling for the use of a product
 12
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
Skin
A
1
B
Vein
2
3
Figure 2.5:
Three stages in the use of a venﬂon catheter for injecting a polymer tube in a vein.
(1) A metal needle labeled
A
penetrates the skin and guides a soft polymer tube labled
B
into
the vein. (2) The metal needle is retracted and disposed of, leaving the polymer tube in the vein.
(3) The polymer tube is ready for use.
and interact with that product is typically carried out by the marketing department, but personal
experiences of the designers will often lead to better results. Many companies therefore encour-
age their designers to directly meet users in order to understand their needs and constraints as
well as how the users will actually interact with the product. User contact is also valuable for
getting feedback on design proposals comprising sketches and/or prototypes.
An example of re-design is furnished by new types of the venﬂon catheter. A soft polymer
tube in the venﬂon catheter is injected into a vein with the help of a stiﬀ metal needle, as shown
in Fig.
2.5
. The metal needle is retracted after the polymer tube is in place and is then disposed
of. Nurses revealed in interviews that the retraction as well as the disposal of the metal needle
are problematic for them. Not only have two extra processes to be carried out, but the sharp
needle also represents a hazard. For this reason, the venﬂon catheter is nowadays equipped with
a small safety device which prevents the nurse from touching the needle tip after it has been
retracted.
When analyzing the needs and constraints during a design activity, it can be advantageous
to meet not only the direct users but also other stakeholders such as sales personnel, repair and
maintenance personnel, and other persons who will come in contact with the product. Face-to-
face interviews, questionnaires requiring both qualitative and quantitative answers, and personal
observations provide insights. Personal experience of the product can also beneﬁt similarly, but
it also carries the risk of introducing bias. The observations and experiences of a designer are
not necessarily the same as those of users. Observations are valuable since they reveal the true
behavior of a user. When interviewed, users tend to give more favorable descriptions of their use
patterns.
 2.4. DESIGN PROCESS
13
The results obtained from the analysis of user needs and existing products are described in
a user-need document. This document can include information on the actual use (and misuse) of
the existing products and the context of use. Sometimes, the context is explained using personas
which are descriptions of typical users and their use patterns.
2.4.2
FUNCTION ANALYSIS
A way to stimulate creativity and generate new and better ways of solving problems is to for-
mulate an abstract description of how a product functions. Instead of describing a product as an
assemblage of its components, it can be described as a set of abstract functions. Another advan-
tage is to avoid product ﬁxation which is a risk when the names of previously used components
are used. If a product is described in terms directly coupled to a speciﬁc action or form, the
designer may become ﬁxated on a speciﬁc solution and ﬁnd it diﬃcult to imagine alternatives.
For example, a concrete functional description such as “drive a person from point A to point
B” will ﬁxate the designer in thinking of vehicles, whereas the abstract functional description
“transport a person from point A to point B” will foster more open thinking so that a wider
palette of solutions can emerge, e.g., conveyer belts and horseback riding.
A product function is normally formulated using a verb/noun combination, such as “con-
taining a liquid” or “cutting a piece of paper.” A complete description of the functions of and
within a product can be made using a functions-means tree diagram [ , ]. The sole trapezoid
1 9
at the top of the diagram describes the main function that justiﬁes the reason why the product
exists or should exist, whereas sub-functions describe what the constituent elements do. Means
are physical manifestations that carry out a function. Both functions and means are explained in
general terms without considering details such as shape or dimension. Figure
2.6
is a functions-
means tree diagram in which the main function and sub-functions pertinent to drug delivery are
identiﬁed along with the various means to accomplish each function. Note a diﬀerence in the
way functions and means are described. All of the associated sub-functions are required for the
realization of the main function. The more means that are recorded under a function, the more
numerous are the ways of realizing that function.
A functional surface identiﬁes where a speciﬁc function resides within the product [ ].
9
A functional surface is typically marked on a sketch of the design object using hatched lines, as
illustrated in Fig.
2.7
. The ﬁgure shows that the two knife edges in a pair of scissors can be
marked with hatched lines to indicate where the cutting function resides. Similarly, the holding
function resides in a handle. The hatched lines do not invoke speciﬁc shapes, thus leaving the
design assignment more open to innovation. A functional surface indicates the existence of
an interface from the product to something else.
Another notion used to describe the functionality of a product in an abstract way is that
of an organ [
11
]. Like functional surfaces, an organ does not include information about shape
and materials, but it does describe in abstract terms how a function is carried out. Two or more
 14
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
Using vacuum
With pressure
Tearing process
Cutting process
Use impulse
Oral
intake
Injection
through the skin
Absorption
through the skin
Stretch skin
To
position
To
ﬁxate skin
To
penetrate skin
Reduce
resistance
Prevent
buckling
Initiate
fracture
Propagate
fracture
To deliver
medicine
To transfer
liquid
Figure 2.6:
A functions-means tree diagram for ways of delivering medicine inside a patient.
Each trapezoidal block contains a function, each rectangular block a means.
Connecting
organ
Holding
surface
2 cutting surfaces
=
cutting organ
Figure 2.7:
Examples of functional surfaces and organs for a pair of scissors.
functional surfaces can be combined into an organ. For example, the two cutting surfaces in a
pair of scissors form a cutting organ.
Another example of an organ is the sealing organ in a container such as a bottle or a jar. A
sealing organ can be realized as a lid with sealing surfaces in the lid and on the container. Using
the term “lid” will automatically bring up mental pictures of existing solutions for bottles and
jars. But referring to a “sealing organ” instead will make it easier to think freely of conceptually
 2.4. DESIGN PROCESS
15
diﬀerent solutions. The designer could then propose a ﬂexible bottle where the opening is closed
like a bag or the sealing organ could be a valve.
2.4.3
DESIGN BRIEF AND PRODUCT SPECIFICATION
A design assignment is typically speciﬁed using two diﬀerent documents: the design brief
and the product specification. The design brief is a visionary document that explains the
context of the intended product and how future users will beneﬁt, without going into details of
the speciﬁcation. The design brief is targeted toward the conceptual-design phase discussed in
Section
2.4.4
.
The product speciﬁcation includes more detailed descriptions and is targeted toward the
design phases that follow the conceptual-design phase. The product speciﬁcation can be formu-
lated in various ways. In the performance-speciﬁcation approach [ ], several requirements are
1
formulated, e.g., the performance metrics that the product must satisfy and the performance
characteristics that it must exhibit. For instance, the product must be manufactured in a certain
range of colors and/or that it must be small enough to be stored in a standard storage space. The
performance-speciﬁcation approach is useful as it delivers a checklist to ensure that a design
proposal is within acceptable limits. However, this approach is less helpful when comparing
diﬀerent design proposals and existing solutions.
The product-speciﬁcation approach [
10
] overcomes that problem. In this approach, both
requirements and criteria are stated. The requirements are ﬁxed and must be met by the design
proposal; otherwise, the design proposal is unviable. The criteria are used to compare diﬀerent
design proposals using evaluation matrixes (Section
2.4.5
) and need to be formulated to indicate
a desirable direction but not set limits. For a new toothbrush as an example, the requirements
could include maximum dimensions and color; the criteria could specify that the toothbrush
should be pleasant to the mouth, be easy to clean, and have a low weight.
2.4.4
CONCEPTUAL DESIGN
Conceptual design is the creative process of generating ideas for solving the overall design
problem and ﬁnding partial solutions to each of the functional challenges identiﬁed in the
functions-means tree diagram.
A typical way to come up with ideas is to form a brainstorming team. There are many prac-
tical approaches [ ] for brainstorming, but all have in common that as large a number of ideas
1
be generated as possible and that criticism of ideas be avoided during brainstorming sessions.
Diﬀerent brainstorming approaches introduce diﬀerent ways of viewing the design problem;
hence, using several diﬀerent approaches increases the number of ideas.
Brainstorming can be done by single persons on their own, but doing it together with
other people will drastically increase the chance of ﬁnding new ideas because participants will
inspire each other. Also, the brainstorming session can have many diﬀerent formats. One format
involves a whiteboard on which a moderator writes up all the ideas that the participants propose.
 16
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
In this way, a participant needs to articulate each of his/her ideas so that it is intelligible to
the moderator, which also facilitates the uptake of that idea by other participants to generate
additional as well as downstream ideas. Another brainstorming format lets each participant write
down their ideas on colored post-it notes that are then stuck on a whiteboard. The advantage
of this format is the delivery of multiple ideas by each participant, but there is a risk that the
participants do not see the ideas of others and do not use those ideas to generate more ideas.
Brainstorming is a creative idea-generation method whereby the participants are not re-
quired to follow rigid rules or constraints. In contrast, systematic idea-generation methods set
rigid rules for the participants, those rules possibly stimulating the participants to examine is-
sues that they would not have otherwise thought of. Examples of systematic idea-generation
methods include analysis of existing or competing solutions, TRIZ, and biologically inspired
design.
Analysis of existing or competing solutions requires identiﬁcation of their weaknesses and
strengths so that a comparative assessment may be made of the opportunities oﬀered by each.
TRIZ is the Russian acronym for the Theory of Inventive Problem Solving which is a
method for developing innovative solutions [
12
]. It is based on a large (
39

39
) matrix of con-
tradictory features (e.g., larger in volume but lighter in weight). Each ﬁeld in the matrix contains
a list of possible solutions developed from analyses of very large number of patents.
Biologically inspired design emerges from the thought that the bioworld oﬀers a palette of
solutions to numerous technological problems. A function analysis must be made of a candidate
structure or process in the bioworld, the relevant principles must be extracted from that analysis,
and ﬁnally those principles must be applied to the problem being addressed in the design activity.
It is important to diﬀerentiate between ideas and concepts. An idea in creative design
work is basically just a principle for how to solve a problem. Application of that principle in a
speciﬁc context transforms the idea into a concept that satisﬁes the context-speciﬁc constraints
and conditions. For example, the idea of using a lid to seal a container becomes a concept in the
context of closing a beer bottle, a context-speciﬁc constraint being that the lid must be able to
withstand the pressure within the bottle.
Conceptual design normally starts by an examination of partial solutions to each of the
functions required in the product. It is assumed that the superposition principle applies so the
partial solutions can be combined to form the overall solution. One way of combining partial
solutions into an overall solution is by using a morphology chart [ ]. This chart is a table con-
1
taining lists of possible partial solutions for each of the functions required in the product. The
partial solutions can be described in words but even better with small icons for easier communi-
cation within the design team. A candidate overall solution can be formulated by selecting one
partial solution for each function.
 2.4. DESIGN PROCESS
17
2.4.5
CONCEPT EVALUATION
The diverse concepts gathered for a given design activity can be comparatively assessed in dif-
ferent ways. Often, the concepts in the form of prototypes can be ranked by major stakehold-
ers including prospective users, who can also provide feedback in the form of written and oral
comments. A risk in this type of assessment is that the evaluation may be based on parame-
ters other than what is important for the product. For example, a poorly produced prototype
could be ranked poorly even though the underlying concept could lead to superior performance.
To avoid such biased evaluations, the major criteria must be clearly formulated in the product
speciﬁcation and used for structuring the interviews with stakeholders and users.
A good tool for concept evaluation is the evaluation matrix which can be one of two
types [ ]:
1
(i) the comparison matrix also referred to as the Pugh matrix and
(ii) the rating matrix also called the weighted-objective-method matrix.
The comparison matrix compares each concept with a reference product which is typically an
existing product. For every criterion in the product speciﬁcation, each concept is rated better
(
C
1
), worse (
1
), or similar ( ) to the reference product and the ratings are added to produce
0
the overall rating for the concept. The major advantage of the comparison matrix is its simplicity
which makes it easy to understand and discuss its results. A limitation is that all criteria need to
be of equal importance since they are weighted equally.
That limitation is taken care of in the rating matrix. Each criterion is given a weight
w
de-
pending on its importance. For every criterion in the product speciﬁcation, each concept is given
a numerical score. The overall rating for the concept is found by multiplying the score numbers
with the weight for each criterion and adding the numbers together. The rating matrix should
produce a better comparison of the diverse concepts than the comparison matrix. However, the
rating matrix is more complicated than the comparison matrix, and stakeholders and users may
ﬁnd it harder to understand and accept the outcomes of a comparison.
2.4.6
TOWARD DETAILED DESIGN
What has been described so far in this chapter is normally referred to as conceptual design. The
results are design concepts describing the product at a general level without going into detail
about materials, shapes, and dimensions. Conceptual-design proposals are often made as hand
drawings to signal that they are not ﬁnished and many details can still be altered. The more
detailed design work is done thereafter: the product embodiment is carefully planned, typically
using software for computer-aided design; precise dimensions are determined; tolerances are
added; materials are selected; and manufacturing techniques are speciﬁed.
Besides drawings by hand and the more detailed drawings produced using computer-aided
design tools, physical models are often made. Depending on their ﬁdelity and purpose, physical
models are referred to using diﬀerent terms. A rudimentary model using rough materials such as
 18
2. WHAT IS DESIGN?
cardboard, clay, and paper is typically called a mock-up. It serves to demonstrate only a few rele-
vant aspects of the product such as physical size and how it interfaces to other products. When a
physical model appears close to the ﬁnal product, it is referred to as a visual model. Another type
of physical model is a functional model, which only serves to demonstrate that a given principle
and embodiment will actually fulﬁll the requirements. Finally, prototypes are traditionally used
to denote models that comes very close to the ﬁnal product but are typically made as one-oﬀs.
However, the terminology is drifting and many designers use the term prototype as a synonym
for a mock-up or a functional model.
While all of these more detailed design activities are important elements in the overall
design process, we will not go into more detail with them in this book. Biologically inspired
design is typically incorporated in the conceptual-design phase.
2.5
REFERENCES
[1] N. Cross,
Engineering Design Methods—Strategies for Product Design
, Wiley, Chichester,
UK, 2008. , , , ,
5 6 7 9 13 15 16 17
,
,
,
[2] B. R. Lawson, Cognitive strategies in architectural design,
Ergonomics
, 22:59–68, 1979.
DOI: 10.1080/00140137908924589 6
.
[3] N. Cross,
Design Thinking: Understanding how Designers Think and Work
, Berg, Oxford,
UK, 2011.
DOI: 10.5040/9781474293884 6
.
[4] D. Adriaens, Evomimetics: The biomimetic design thinking 2.0,
Proceedings of SPIE
,
10965:1096509, 2019.
DOI: 10.1117/12.2514049 7
.
[5] N. Eldredge and S. J. Gould, Punctuated equilibria: An alternative to phyletic gradual-
ism,
Models in Paleobiology
, T. J. M. Schopf, Ed., pages 82–115, Freeman Cooper, San
Francisco, CA, 1972.
7
[6] M. J. Benton and P. N. Pearson, Speciation in the fossil record,
Trends in Ecology and
Evolution
, 16:405–411, 2001.
DOI: 10.1016/s0169-5347(01)02149-8 7
.
[7] C. M. Christensen, M. Raynor, and R. McDonald, What is disruptive innovation?,
Har-
vard Business Review
, 93(12):44–53, 2015.
7
[8] G. Pahl, W. Beitz, J. Feldhusen, and K.-H. Grote,
Engineering Design: A Systematic Ap-
proach
, 3rd ed., Springer, London, UK, 2007.
DOI: 10.1007/978-1-84628-319-2 7 8
. ,
[9] E. Tjalve,
A Short Course in Industrial Design
, Butterworth, London, UK, 1979.
DOI:
10.1016/C2013-0-00824-9 9 10 13
. ,
,
[10] M. M. Andreasen and L. Hein,
Integrated Product Development
, IFS (Publications) Ltd.,
Kempston, UK, 1987.
10 11 15
,
,
