See discussions, stats, and author profiles for this publication at: 
https://www.researchgate.net/publication/268506270
Function-Based Biologically-Inspired Design
Chapter
 · July 2014
DOI: 10.1007/978-1-4471-5248-4_5
CITATIONS
20
READS
2,026
3 authors
, including:
Some of the authors of this publication are also working on these related projects:
Interprofessional Innovations in a MakerSpace CUR 2016
 
View project
A Quantitative Theory for Technology Evolution and Innovation
 
View project
Jacquelyn K. Nagel
James Madison University
90
 
PUBLICATIONS
   
808
 
CITATIONS
   
SEE PROFILE
Daniel A. Mcadams
Texas A&M University
173
 
PUBLICATIONS
   
4,279
 
CITATIONS
   
SEE PROFILE
All content following this page was uploaded by 
Jacquelyn K. Nagel
 on 19 November 2014.
The user has requested enhancement of the downloaded file.
 Chapter 5 - Function-Based Biologically-
Inspired Design 
Jacquelyn K.S. Nagel 
Department of Engineering, James Madison University Harrisonburg, VA, USA 
Robert B. Stone 
School of Mechanical, Industrial and Manufacturing Engineering, Oregon State University 
Corvallis, OR, USA 
Daniel A. McAdams 
Department of Mechanical Engineering, Texas A&M University, College Station, TX, USA 
Abstract   
A “big picture” approach to a systematic, function-based biologically-
inspired design is presented in this chapter.  The approach supports two different 
starting, or perhaps motivating, points: a customer need motivated product design 
or a biological system motivated product opportunity.  Both approaches rely on a 
designer’s ability to create a functional model that either captures customer needs 
or represents the biological system of interest.  This methodology relies directly 
on  the  designer’s  ability  to  make  connections  between  dissimilar  domain  infor-
mation.  Following presentation of the methodology are two validation approach-
es.  One examines current biologically-inspired products either in production or 
presented in literature to demonstrate that the systematic design methodology for 
biologically-inspired  can  reproduce  the  existing  design.   The  second  validation 
exercise investigates three needs-based design problems that lead to plausible bio-
logically-inspired solutions.   
 
 2  
5.1 Introduction 
 
Biological organisms, phenomena and strategies, herein referred to as biological 
systems, provide a rich set of examples that can be used to inspire engineering in-
novation. Bioinspired, or biomimetic, designs are publicly viewed as creative and 
novel solutions to human problems. Moreover, some biomimetic designs have be-
come so commonplace that it is hard to image life without them (e.g. velcro, air-
planes). Although the bioinspired solutions are innovative and useful, the majority 
of inspiration taken from nature has happened by chance observation or dedicated 
study  of  a  specific  biological  entity  (e.g.,  gecko).    This  reveals  a  fundamental 
problem of working across the engineering and biological domains. The effort and 
time required to become a competent engineering designer creates significant ob-
stacles to becoming sufficiently knowledgeable about biological systems (the con-
verse can also be said). This research aims to go beyond the element of chance, 
reduce  the  amount  of  time  and  effort  required  to  develop  bioinspired  solutions, 
and bridge the seemingly immense disconnect between the engineering and bio-
logical domains. 
This chapter presents a comprehensive design approach, including a methodol-
ogy and supporting tools, that integrates with function-based design techniques to 
facilitate biologically-inspired design. As a function-based method it offers several 
advantages:  Archival  and  transmittal  of  design  information;  reduces  fixation  on 
aesthetic features or a particular physical solution; allows one to define the scope 
or boundary of the design problem as broad or narrow as necessary; and encour-
ages one to draw upon experience, knowledge stored in a database or through cre-
ative methods during concept generation. Function, as used in systematic design, 
is recognized as a way to connect nature and engineering through a commonality. 
This approach addresses the knowledge requirement problem of working across 
the biology and engineering domains and, through functional modeling, offers the 
aforementioned advantages.  
A  design  methodology  that  facilitates  systematic  biologically-inspired  design 
from a problem-driven or solution-driven perspective is given.  Following a tradi-
tional  design  approach,  the  problem-driven  perspective  begins  from  customer 
needs  or  a  given  problem  to  solve.  Following  curiosity,  the  solution-driven  ap-
proach encourages a designer to explore a biological system of interest to learn 
more about it or develop an innovative solution that could potentially be applied to 
an existing problem. The methodology also prescribes the tools of the framework 
to use while guiding the designer through the steps. Although systematic, the de-
sign methodology is also versatile by providing a designer multiple avenues that 
lead to a biologically-inspired design.  
Biologically-inspired design is a young field within engineering design.  Con-
sequently,  validation  of  the  design  methodology  is  challenging.    Thus,  two  ap-
proaches  to  validation  are  pursued.    One  examines  current  biologically-inspired 
 3 
products either in production or presented in literature to demonstrate that the sys-
tematic design methodology for biologically-inspired can reproduce the existing 
design.  The second validation exercise investigates three needs-based design case 
studies that lead to plausible biologically-inspired solutions.  The needs-based de-
sign  case  studies  demonstrate  the  systematic  design  approach  to  biologically-
inspired design from the problem-driven perspective.  A reference to a case study 
from  the  solution-driven  perspective  is  also  provided.   The  thought  processes, 
model iterations and connections that are the leaps that enable the ingenuity of the 
nature to be discovered and adapted for use in engineered systems are also pre-
sented.   
Using functional representation and abstraction to describe biological systems 
presents  the  natural  designs  in  an  engineering  context  and  allows  designers  to 
make connections between biological and engineered systems. Thus, the biologi-
cal  information  is  accessible  to  engineering  designers  with  varying  biological 
knowledge,  but  a  common  understanding  of  engineering  design  methodologies.  
By creating a bridge between the two domains through the perspective of function, 
engineers can leverage the elegant designs found in the world around them. This 
work demonstrates the feasibility of using systematic design for the discovery of 
innovative engineering designs without requiring expert-level knowledge, but ra-
ther broad knowledge of many fields. 
5.2 Framework to Support Method 
Various tools and techniques combine or interact to support the overall systematic 
biologically-inspired design methodology.  The engineering-to-biology thesaurus 
(see Chapter 4) is the backbone of this framework, as it assists with modeling bio-
logical systems and searching for inspiration or solutions.  Consequently, the the-
saurus also assists with concept generation, both directly and indirectly.  Indirect 
assistance is through the modeling method and organized search tool, and direct 
assistance is through designer knowledge of a biological process (e.g., the conver-
sion of sunlight to sugars) that could solve a set of design needs of a product.  The 
following section makes this indirect assistance more explicit. 
A framework, by definition, is an arrangement of parts that provides a system 
or concept a basic form [1].  In the framework developed here, the parts are identi-
fy, translate, represent and conceptualize.  The system or concept being supported 
is  the  systematic  biologically-inspired  design  methodology.    What  makes  this 
framework particularly useful for design is the flexibility a designer is afforded 
when working toward a biologically-inspired solution.  Each tool and technique 
can be used individually and in multiple combinations.  Prior work has shown how 
the  engineering-to-biology  thesaurus  integrates  with  and  improves  organized 
search tools [2-4], supports biological functional modeling method [4,2,5] and in-
tegrates with concept generation approaches [6].  Specific interaction benefits are 
 4  
pointed out in the Venn diagram of Figure 5.1.  Using all four parts results in sys-
tematic biologically-inspired design.  
 
Fig. 5.1. Framework Details
  
 
Knowledge requirements for working between domains can be alleviated with 
design methods that integrate the existing engineering design tools.  This frame-
work alleviates knowledge requirements by integrating the function-based design 
methodologies, in particular, the systematic design process defined by Pahl and 
Beitz [7].  The framework also leverages existing design tools to further integrate 
within function-based design methodologies, as shown in Table 5.1.  The existing 
design tools include a functional modeling lexicon, a repository of design infor-
mation, and automated concept generation methods.   
Table 5.1. Framework Integration with Existing Design Tools  
 
Framework Tool or  
Technique
 
Existing Tool Leveraged  
by Framework
 
Engineering-to-Biology Thesaurus
 
Functional Basis
 
 5 
Biological Functional Modeling Method
 
Functional Basis
 
Organized Search Tool
 
Functional Basis,  Design Repository
 
Concept Generation Approaches
 
MEMIC, Automated Morphological Matrix, Design 
Repository
 
5.3 Biologically-Inspired Design Methodology 
In this section the overall design methodology is given.   In support of the system-
atic  biologically-inspired  design  methodology,  several  separate  techniques  coa-
lesce to guide the designer from initial curiosity or customer needs to complete 
concept [8].  The framework for making connections between biology and engi-
neering is presented first followed by the design methodology.   
Two holistic approaches by the Biomimicry Institute [9] and Helms et al. [10] 
offer a process for designers to follow, from a biology perspective and an engi-
neering  perspective,  respectively,  and  a  database  of  biological  information  that 
supports biologically-inspired design.  These approaches, however, do not offer a 
framework of design tools that integrate with the design process to support the de-
signer throughout biologically-inspired design. This chapter addresses that gap by 
offering  a  systematic  methodology,  with  both  problem-  and  solution-based  ap-
proaches, along with a framework of supporting design tools that integrate with 
established function-based, engineering design methodologies.  
The systematic design methodology of this chapter provides enough structure 
to assist with the bioinspired design process without hindering the creativity and 
inventiveness of the designer.  Rather, this method is intended to foster and guide 
the abilities of the designer and encourage objective evaluation of results.  The 
systematic  approaches  of  this  method  are  further  intended  to  render  designing 
based on biological inspiration comprehensible and steer the efforts of designers 
down purposeful paths. 
5.3.1 Making Connections 
This research relies on the designer’s ability to identify and formulate connections 
between biological and engineering domains.  Just as there are different learning 
styles, there are multiple ways to make connections.  Analogies [11-23] are the 
most widely used and have multiple forms.  Direct, indirect, and compound analo-
gies have all been used to connect a biological system to an engineering solution.  
A direct analogy mimics the biological system one-to-one.  An indirect analogy 
uses  the  biological  system  to  spur  analogies  for  inspiration  but  does  not  mimic 
every aspect of the biological system.  A compound analogy is the combination of 
multiple biological system attributes that lead to analogous engineered systems.  
 6  
The level of difficulty in accessing and transferring an analogy is largely depend-
ent on how remote or close the distance between the domains is [24].  Because 
much of nature exhibits functionality and behavior in a comparable context to en-
gineering, analogies with engineering are possible.  To exemplify the connection 
making process for analogies, consider a few textual examples. 
A micro flow detection sensor directly mimics the physiology and morphology 
of  hair  cells  that  make  up  the  lateral  line  system  in  a  fish.    The  connection  is 
through the principle of a bending moment that is created from perpendicular flow 
against vertical hair cells.  Direct analogy mimicry is achieved through fabrication 
of  “hair-like”  vertical  structures  on  the  end  of  a  horizontal  cantilever  beam 
[25,26].  
An indirect analogy bioinspired design was created between the common strain 
gage and the physiology of the campaniform sensillum or flexible exocuticle that 
many insects possess.  An elliptical opening in the insect’s cuticle, which is cov-
ered by a thin membrane layer, senses deformation because of the stress concen-
tration [27,28].  The connection for this system is that the opening causes mechan-
ical coupling and global amplification to occur.  Mimicry is achieved by optically 
measuring the stress concentration at a circular or elliptical hole in a rigid material 
when pressure is applied; resulting in a novel sensor that can sense strain in all di-
rections (360°) [29].   
In the case of designing an electronic display that can be viewed in bright sun-
light, a bioinspired compound analogy was used to solve the problem.  For the 
display problem, hummingbird feather and morpho-butterfly wing attributes were 
combined to develop a solution [30].  Hummingbird feathers contain a series of al-
ternating  layers  of  thin-films  with  different  thicknesses  instead  of  the  intricate 
christmas tree-like structures within an air gap that butterfly wings possess.  The 
connections here are the air gap and “thin-film like” structures, which are readily 
used  in  electronics  processing  today.    Adding  an  air  gap  between  thin-films  of 
varying thicknesses provided the right inspiration to develop the BrightView pro-
ject [30]. 
A designer must also be aware of analogies that hurt the design or ones that are 
overly complicated.  Consider the biological phenomenon of abscission.  When a 
leaf of a plant is damaged it stops the flow of auxin and allows abscisic acid to 
dominate, thus forming a seal around the base of the leaf stem and over a period of 
time the leaf falls off [31].  This biological system was used to inspire a solution 
to the problem of tiny parts sticking to a robot gripper in a microassembly process 
[32].   
Considering indirect analogy for this case allowed the researchers to develop a 
sacrificial tool assembly.  To highlight the analogy, consider the gripper as analo-
gous to the plant, the sacrificial part of the tool analogous to the abscission zone, 
and the tiny screw as analogous to the leaf that is released.  Separation is achieved 
through the breakdown of the sacrificial part of the tool (abscission zone).  Notice, 
liquids that are analogous to auxin and abscisic acid are not present in the final de-
sign.   
 7 
Developing  a  direct  analogy  of  abscission  would  require  a  flowing  chemical 
that secures and releases the tiny screw.  Release of the tiny screw would occur 
some time after the chemical flow stops and a chemical reaction takes place to 
loosen the part from the gripper.  The indirect analogy that disregards liquids is 
the preferred solution concept.  Therefore, another analogy form should be con-
sidered if the results lead to a bad design. 
Two other approaches to formulating connections are through first principles 
[33-36] and metaphors [37-40].  Analysis of physiology, structure or behavior can 
lead to a connection made through first principles.  Physical laws and concepts, 
such as the conservation of energy, that govern science as we know it also apply to 
natural systems.   
Identifying a first principle shared by both domains leads to a connection and 
possibly innovation.  Consider how ducks and other birds regulate their tempera-
ture during the winter to stay alive.  The principle of heat exchange between the 
body and the legs is carried out to reduce the amount of heat lost though blood that 
is circulated through the legs [34].  To date, metaphors for biologically-inspired 
design have only been documented for architectural structures [41].  The multiple 
approaches to formulating connections allow a designer to discover and become 
inspired in a manner that best suits him or her.  
5.3.2 The Methodology 
A pictorial representation of the method is given in Figure 5.2.  The flower is used 
to  show  that  the  methodology  is  an  organic  process  that  has  systematic  design 
roots.  Each of the steps is discussed in greater detail below.    The majority of, if 
not all, design processes are iterative and this methodology follows the same con-
vention.  Cues for when to iterate are provided.  Furthermore, the design method-
ology here should not be viewed as a rigid sequence in which one must follow 
each minute detailed step.  Rather, it should be viewed as a starting point or a set 
of guidelines that aim to arrive at a biologically-inspired design.  
 
 8  
 
 
Fig.  5.2.  An  Overview  of  the  Five  Steps  of  the  Systematic  Biologically-Inspired  Design 
Methodology.
  
Figure 5.3 summarizes the avenues of the problem-driven approach that close-
ly follow traditional systematic design and the avenues of the problem-driven ap-
 9 
proach that start from a known biological solution are summarized in Figure 5.4.  
Figure 5.5 is a flow chart of the solution-driven approach that starts from curiosi-
ty.  Also, the parts of the framework and existing design tools used in each step of 
the method are made explicit in Table 5.2.  
 
Table 5.2. Framework Parts and Existing Design Tools Used in Each Step of the Methodol-
ogy. 
 
Tools 
↓
 
Steps 
→
 
Needs or  
Curiosity
 
Decompose
 
Query
 
Make  
Connections
 
Create 
Concepts
 
Framework
 
E2B 
Thesaurus
 
X
 
X
 
X
 
X
 
 
Search Tool
 
X
 
 
X
 
 
 
Biological Func. 
Model
 
 
X
 
X
 
X
 
X
 
Biological Con. 
Gen.
 
 
 
X
 
 
X
 
Existing
 
Design  
Repository
 
 
 
X
 
X
 
X
 
Functional 
Basis
 
X
 
X
 
X
 
 
 
MEMIC
 
 
 
X
 
 
 
Auto Morph 
Matrix
 
 
 
X
 
 
 
 
Step 1: Needs or Curiosity 
Initially, A designer can choose to start from a traditional set of customer needs or 
explore a curiosity.  These two routes are identified as problem-driven and solu-
tion-driven,  respectively.    Taking  the  problem-driven  route  means  the  designer 
must gather a set of needs, requirements and constrains.  Many sources exist to aid 
the designer with proper needs gathering [35,42-46].   Identifying customer needs 
is the most critical part of the design process as they form the basis for device 
functionality and specifications.  Taking the solution-driven route means a design-
er already knows of an interesting biological system in which he or she would like 
to investigate.  Thus, the focus is on finding an application for the principles and 
concepts exhibited in that biological system rather that finding principles to solve 
an engineering need. However, the organized search tool can be used to find a bio-
logical system to investigate initially. 
 
 10  
Step 2: Decompose 
The second step involves decomposing the needs or interesting biological system 
into, first, a black box model and, second, a functional model.  All models created 
with this method use the Functional Basis modeling lexicon.  With regards to tra-
ditional systematic design, the black box aims to abstract the overall function of 
the device that is to be designed.  Whereas for a biological system the black box 
model describes an interesting function, structure, behavior or strategy of the sys-
tem.  Next, the input and output flows to the black box are determined.  These 
flows  are  prompted  by  the  customer  needs  from  the  first  step  or  the 
needs/attributes  of  the  biological  system  needed  to  achieve  the  black  box  func-
tionality.  The next task is to create the functional model.  Decompose the black 
box description into sub-functions connected by flows of energy, material or sig-
nal  [7,35,47-49].    Functional  model  creation  is  often  an  iterative  task.    Before 
moving on to the next step, check to see that all customer needs have been met by 
identifying  the  flows  and  sub-function  chains  that  address  them  [7,35,47-49].  
When following the solution-driven route, the designer can refer to the general bi-
ological modeling methodology presented in [4] for assistance with creating a bio-
logical functional model.  
 
Step 3: Query 
Step three involves querying a knowledge base to identify solutions to each func-
tion/flow pair of the functional model.  Two knowledge bases are required: one 
containing successful engineered systems and the other containing biological sys-
tems.  To integrate with this method, both are indexed by engineering function and 
flow.  The Design Repository  containing descriptive product information serves 
1
as  the  engineered  systems  body  of  knowledge.    It  also  includes  product  infor-
mation  such  as  functionality,  component  parameters,  manufacturing  processes, 
failure, and component connectivity. The Design Repository now contains design 
knowledge of over 113 consumer products and 30 biological systems.  Instead of 
creating  a  large  knowledge  base  containing  functionally  decomposed  biological 
systems, similar to the design repository, an introductory biology textbook serves 
as the biological systems body of knowledge.  Although it is not indexed by engi-
neering function, the engineering-to-biology thesaurus provides a starting point to 
find inspiration with engineering function and flow.  
The tasks that comprise step three begin with using the MEMIC software, or 
automated morphological matrix search tool, to query the Design Repository and 
the organized search software to query the biological corpus.  
Based  on  the  number  of  results  returned  for  engineered  and  biological  solu-
tions,  the  search  may  need  to  be  repeated.    For  engineered  solutions,  it  can  be 
helpful  to  abstract  terms  to  the  next  level  in  the  hierarchy.    For  example,  if 
                                                             
1
 www.designengineeringlab.org 
 11 
transport,
 a tertiary level term, does not return any repository entries then the sec-
 
ondary level term 
transfer
 should be used.  The same approach applies to flows. 
 
Step 4: Make Connections 
Step four involves making connections. Connections through analogies, metaphors 
and first principles assist with bridging the biology and engineering domains. Sec-
tion 5.3.1 contains a thorough discussion of how connections are formulated. 
 
Step 5: Concept Generation 
The fifth step involves performing concept generation and creating biologically-
inspired conceptual solutions.  Concept synthesis involves analysis, reflection and 
synthesis.  Analysis is on the returned engineered and biological solutions from 
Step 3.  Reflection is on the connections to the engineering domain formulated in 
Step 4.  Synthesis is of the existing engineering solutions, engineering solutions 
inspired by biology and inventive solutions inspired by biology to derive a new 
idea. Once synthesis takes place the result will be at least one concept.  Depending 
on the number of solutions returned during Step 3 and the connections made dur-
ing Step 4, multiple concepts may result.  Evaluation of concepts follows system-
atic design; Pugh charts or decision matrices are used to rank concepts and narrow 
the selection to the superior few concepts [35,42-46].  Once a final concept has 
been reached the next phase of systematic design, Detailed Design [7], can initi-
ate. 
 
 12  
 
Fig. 5.3. Flow Chart of the Problem-Driven Approach that Closely Follows Traditional Sys-
tematic Design. 
 13 
 
Fig. 5.4. Flow Chart of the Problem-Driven Approach that Starts from a Known Biological 
Solution. 
 14  
 
Fig. 5.5. Flow Chart of the Solution-Driven Approach. 
 
 15 
5.3.3 Comparison of Methodology Approaches 
Notice that the major difference between the avenues to biologically-inspired de-
sign as shown in Figure 5.3 and 5.4 are within Step 2.  When a designer follows 
traditional systematic design, flow A of Figure 5.3, and decomposes a functional 
model from a black box model, the resultant model is referred to as a conceptual 
functional model.  The conceptual functional model is used to query the engineer-
ing and biology knowledge bases.  In the event that no connections can be formal-
ized, then the designer should return to the query step and try different levels of 
functions and flows.  The same holds true for when no concepts are synthesized. 
Following  flow  B  of  Figure  5.3  instructs  the  designer  to  use  the  organized 
search tool heuristics for the initial query.  Once biological solutions are gathered, 
then the Design Repository is queried to supplement the biological solutions with 
engineering solutions.   One difference here is that the results of the search tool 
should be screened first before moving on.  In the event that no connections can be 
formalized then the designer should return to the query step and try a different 
heuristic.  The same holds true for when no concepts are synthesized. 
If a designer knows of a biological system that can solve the black box func-
tionality then a biological functional model of this system can be created to drive 
the methodology as shown in flow A of Figure 5.4.  In the event that no connec-
tions can be formalized, then the designer should return to the decompose step and 
either modify the biological functional model or choose a different biological sys-
tem for exploration.  The same holds true for when no concepts are synthesized.  
Consider the scenario of when a designer can describe a known biological pro-
cess that solves the black box functionality, as shown in flow B of Figure 5.4.  Us-
ing the biological process as a starting point, the designer can search for biological 
systems that perform that process using the organized search tool.  If the search 
results  are  too  narrow  or  uninspiring,  the  designer  can  use  the  engineering-to-
biology thesaurus to identify new query terms.  Once a biological system is cho-
sen, then the designer can define the biological system with a functional model 
and  use  it  to  discover  engineered  solutions  that  perform  the  same  functions  to 
make connections back to the engineering domain, unless connections are readily 
facilitated.  In the event that no connections can be formalized then the designer 
should return to step two and either choose a different biological system for explo-
ration  or,  if  no  model  was  created,  develop  a  biological  functional.    The  same 
holds true for when no concepts are synthesized.  In both process flows of Figure 
5.4, if the Design Repository results are limited, then the designer should try dif-
ferent levels of functions and flows to broaden the search. 
The  fifth  approach  under  this  methodology,  termed  the  solution-driven  ap-
proach, is driven by curiosity and the possibility of creating an innovative solution 
based on the inspiring biological system that may or may not be fit to a problem.  
The main use for this approach, however, is the creation of archivable biological 
knowledge that is in an engineering context.  This type of knowledge can be re-
 16  
used in future design activities when stored in a knowledge base.  The main tasks 
of this approach, as shown in Figure 5.5, follow the steps of the systematic biolog-
ically-inspired design method.  In the event that no connections can be formalized 
then the designer should return to the decompose step and modify the biological 
functional.  The same holds true for when no concepts are synthesized.  Another 
option is to return to Step 1, choose a different biological system for exploration 
and start over.  Also, if the Design Repository results are meager or non-existent 
then the designer should try different levels of functions and flows to broaden the 
search. 
5.4 Validation of Method 
Validation of the systematic biologically-inspired design methodology is achieved 
through application of the methodology to (1) check if it reproduces existing bio-
mimetic products and (2) identify a closely related development version of a con-
cept through literature review.  Analysis and reproduction of existing biomimetic 
products through primary function allows the verification of the methodology as 
the  result  is  known.    Validating  the  methodology  for  non-existing  biomimetic 
products requires a review of literature  to quantify if the concept variants are real-
istic in some near term form.  Finding a closely related development version of the 
biologically-inspired conceptual design indicates that the concept is feasible.  Sim-
ilarity is based on functionality and components chosen to achieve functionality.  
Six existing biomimetic products are analyzed through application of the meth-
od  to  demonstrate  that  the  method  can  reproduce  what  is  known.    To  further 
demonstrate  the  validity  of  this  method,  three  needs-based  design  problems  are 
presented. The methodology is considered successful when a designer can analyze 
a  biological  system  and  identify  connections  between  biology  and  engineering 
through function that lead to inspiration of a concept.  Further, more detailed vali-
dation cases of how the methodology can result in innovative solutions following 
the problem-driven approach is given in [49] and how the methodology can result 
in an innovative solution following the solution-driven approach is given in [4,49]. 
5.4.1 Proof Through Existing Biomimetic Technology 
The first validation exercise is to analyze existing biomimetic products, apply the 
systematic design methodology and verify that the biological system used to in-
spire the original design is used in the results in such a way that could lead to a re-
production. 
Table 5.3 lists six existing biomimetic products. These technologies represent 
the fields of electrical, civil and mechanical engineering and material science.  The 
 17 
validation studies here relied on technical descriptions of these products found in 
the literature.  From the descriptions, primary function/flow pairs were identified 
and  represented  with  Functional  Basis  terminology.    The  primary  function/flow 
pairs are then used to query the biological knowledge base.   
Both representation and querying utilizes the engineering-to-biology thesaurus.  
If the mimicked biological system is within the query results and described in a 
way that makes a connection and results in a similar concept to the existing bio-
mimetic technology, then it follows that the method can reproduce the design.   
During this validation exercise, AskNature was added to the biological corpus 
knowledge base to augment topical limitations in the corpus. AskNature , is an on-
2
line database that biologists, engineers, designers, chemists, etc. can contribute fo-
cused on biologically inspired design.  
Table 5.3. Analysis of Existing Biomimetic Products to Validate Methodology. 
Existing  
Biomimetic  
Products
 
Mimicked  
Biological  
System
 
Primary  
Function/Flow  
Pair(s)
 
Source
 
Can Method 
Reproduce De-
sign?
 
Walking stick for visually  Echolocation  
impaired that uses sonar
 
of bats
 
Detect Solid
 
Biological 
Corpus
 
Yes
 
Passive heating and cooling 
buildings
 
Termite mounds
 
Regulate Thermal  
Energy, Distribute  
Thermal Energy, 
Distribute Gas, 
Remove Gas
 
Asknature.orgYes
   
Self-cleaning surfaces
 
Lotus
 
Inhibit Solid, 
Inhibit Liquid, 
Decrease Solid
 
Asknature.orgYes
   
Motion detector
 
Compound  
vision
 
Detect Solid, 
Sense Solid
 
Biological 
Corpus
 
Yes
 
Color changing material 
without harmful chemicals
 
Morpho-Butterfly
 
Change  
Visual Signal
 
Asknature.orgYes
   
Microassembly with sacrifi-Abscission of 
cial gripper 
 
plants
 
Separate Solid
 
Biological 
Corpus
 
Yes
 
 
Following the five steps of the methodology, all six existing biomimetic tech-
nologies  were  reproduced.    The  three  found  with  the  organized  search  tool  re-
quired  the  substitution  of  biological  function  and  flow  terms  of  the  thesaurus, 
while the three found within the AskNature database needed substitution of only 
the  flow  term.    Additionally,  other  biological  systems  were  identified  that  also 
                                                             
2
 www.asknature.org 
 18  
solve the function/flow pair, which, if a redesign were undertaken, could result in 
compound analogical design. 
5.4.2 Smart Flooring Case Study 
Validation through exploration of non-existing biomimetic products is performed 
here on a smart flooring application. Consider the following scenario. A customer 
wants  to  create  a  security/surveillance  product  that  looks  like  ordinary  carpet, 
mats,  rugs,  and  etc.  to  detect  intruders,  a  presence  of  something  in  a  room  or 
movement.  Requirements  for  the  smart  flooring  include  a  detection  mechanism 
unseen by human eye, durability, composition of common materials and a quick 
detection response. Also, the system needs to be autonomous.   
The new design should offer advantages over currents systems. Current tagged 
based systems require the user to carry a badge or other device to be tracked or 
monitored and simply removing the trackable item can defeat the system.  Radar 
or similar systems require calibration and an area map to be created.  Each time 
the area layout is changed, the map needs to be updated.  Video surveillance and 
heat signature systems can be very expensive and often require a person to watch 
the real-time video feed.     
These  needs  and  constraints  are  mapped  to  flows  as  shown  in  Table  5.4  to 
complete the first step of the methodology.  Next, the black box model is created 
to guide the decomposition of the flows into a functional model.  Figure 5.6 pro-
vides the black box model.  Figure 5.7 provides the conceptual functional model.  
The  model  of  Figure  5.7  was  created  with  a  boundary  of  the  flooring  in  place, 
electrical energy is supplied to the detection mechanism and when an object or 
human interacts with the flooring a signal is generated.  
Table 5.4. Needs of Smart Flooring Device Mapped to Flows. 
Needs/Constraints
 
Functional Basis Flow
 
Object/Human to detect
 
Solid Material
 
Quick detection response
 
Status Signal
 
System power
 
Electrical Energy
 
 
 
Fig. 5.6. Smart Flooring Black Box Model.
 
 
 19 
 
Fig. 5.7. Smart Flooring Conceptual Functional Model. 
 
From here the search heuristics were applied, following flow chart B of Figure 
5.3.  Using the general inspiration heuristic, several interesting biological systems 
were found to perform the function of 
detect
.  An organized search of a biological 
corpus resulted in the following query results [50]:  
1. The hair cell 
 
2. Electroreceptors found in electric fish 
 
3. Epithelial cells 
 
4. Genes that mark recombinant DNA 
 
5. DNA 
 
6. Why birds flock in large groups 
 
7. Echolocation 
 
8. Carotiod and aortic stretch receptors 
 
9. Membrane receptor proteins 
 
10.Graded action potentials  
Next, following Step 4 of the methodology, the biological systems returned for 
the function of 
detect
 are analyzed to formalize connections.  
Hair cells are analogous to cantilevers and would detect a presence when dis-
turbed.  In a similar manner, the carotid and aortic stretch receptors are analogous 
to  flexible  materials  such  as  polymers.    A  polymer  would  detect  a  disturbance 
when pressure is applied. 
Echolocation is analogous to radar.  Radar is already used to detect objects, 
however, it is not a distributed system, as would be needed for a smart flooring 
concept.  The final connection made from the above list is with the electroreceptor 
of fish.  Electroreceptors generate an electric field for navigation of the environ-
ment, to locate objects, which is also analogous to radar.  Echolocation uses sound 
waves where electrolocation uses electric waves. 
Now that the query results have been analyzed and reflected upon to get to es-
tablish  connections  between  biology  and  engineering,  the  next  task,  following 
flow chart B of Figure 5.3, is to query the engineering knowledge base and sup-
plement the biologically-inspired solutions with engineering solutions to complete 
the design.  The returned engineering solutions, shown in Table 5.5, are then syn-
 20  
thesized.  Functional  representation  enables  a  thorough  understanding  of  the  re-
quirements while decreasing the tendency of designers to fixate on some particular 
physical solution for a problem. Therefore, this approach is form independent and 
relies on the designer’s ability to develop a reasonable form for the concept. With 
the components of Table 5.5 and the established analogies, the final step of con-
cept generation can begin.  
    The biological system of the hair cell prompts two concept variants.  Both con-
cept variants use wires and circuits boards to perform the functions involving elec-
trical energy and would likely be powered by an external, low voltage power sup-
ply. Regardless of the concept, a flexible circuitry layer and buffer layer would 
need  to  be  underneath  the  visible  flooring  layer  to  connect  the  array  to  a  pro-
cessing unit and to protect the underlying circuitry, respectively. These are repre-
sented in the concept sketch close-up views as the orange layer between two black 
layers.  
Wanting to remotely monitor a space means that the solution for indicate status 
signal must also be remotely located to the smart flooring. For both concept vari-
ants, the LCD screen is a viable option as the detection mechanism will produce a 
measurable result, which can be displayed on the LCD screen. The concept vari-
ants below focus on the biologically-inspired detection mechanism, therefore the 
power supply and LCD screen are not shown. 
Recall that the critical need is unseen by the human eye. Considering the tactile 
response  of  the  hair  cell  as  a  cantilever  and  flooring  shaped  as  individual  tiles, 
each tile could act as one cantilever to detect a load. The array of cantilever load 
sensors would then sense a pressure differential as a person walks across the smart 
flooring. A spring is added to the design to keep the tile from collapsing, while al-
lowing the cantilever bend. A concept sketch is shown in Figure 5.8.  Detail de-
sign would need to be completed to determine the cantilever material that would 
best respond and last in a high traffic environment. 
Table 5.5. Engineering Solutions Mapped to Function/Flow Pairs. 
 
Function/ Flow
 
Engineering Solution
 
Import/ electrical energy
 
Battery, circuit board, electric motor, electric wire, electric switch
 
Regulate/ electrical energy
 
Actuation lever, capacitor, circuit board, automobile distributor, 
electric switch, heating element, transistor, transformer, thermo-
stat, regulator, volume knob
 
Transfer/ electrical energy
 
Battery, circuit board, electric wire, electric motor, electric socket, 
electric plate, electric switch, heating element, usb cable, light fix-
ture, speaker
 
Transmit/ electrical energy
 
Electrical wire, battery contacts, motor controller
 
Detect/ solid material
 
Read head, line guide
 
Indicate/ status signal
 
Light, tube, displacement gauge, LCD screen
 
Export/ electrical energy
 
Circuit board, electric wire, electric switch
 
 
 21 
 
Fig. 5.8. Concept Variant One for Smart Flooring.
 
The second concept variant simultaneously exploits the tactile response of the 
hair cell and the carotid and aortic stretch receptors and the change in electric po-
tential from the sensory cells. Hair cells are vertical structures, while stretch recep-
tors are found in multiple orientations. Taking inspiration from the hair cell and 
stretch receptor morphology leads to a detector design that is comprised of a verti-
cal structure that can be stretched in multiple orientations. 
Offering flexibility and ruggedness for repeated deflection, this detector design 
could work for woven flooring such as carpet. Taking inspiration from the sensory 
cells, flexion of the carpet fibers would result in a change of resistivity, similar to 
a strain gage, or generate a voltage by the principle of piezoelectricity. Polyamide 
is a high performance synthetic polymer and is commonly used in textiles. Fabri-
cating polyamide tubes with a conductive gel or paste that can be woven into car-
pet to form an array would achieve the biologically-inspired design. Materials re-
search would need to be completed to determine if the polyamide and conductive 
gel or paste would last in a high traffic environment.  
Alternatively, conductive thread, another detector solution that can be stretched 
in multiple orientations, could easily be woven into carpet and offer a change of 
resistivity. Conductive thread exists and is used in garments and accessories that 
merge technology into clothing. Materials research would need to be completed to 
determine if the conductive thread would provide a significant change in resistive-
ly or conductivity once woven into a carpet.  A concept sketch is shown in Figure 
5.9. Shaded strands in the close-up view of the carpet fibers in Figure 5.9 repre-
sent durable feedback elements woven into the carpet, providing hidden sensing 
capabilities. 
 
 22  
 
Fig. 5.9. Concept Variant Two for Smart Flooring. 
 
 
Looking to literature for a similar surveillance device uncovered a handful of 
attempts to create a “smart” floor or flooring.  The first concept described above, 
individual tiles that detect a load placed in an array, has been done.  Richardson et 
al. have developed hexagonal, puzzle-like pieces called nodes that are placed in an 
array to detect pressure [51].  Their tiles contain force sensitive resistors and inter-
lock to form a self-organizing network that passes data to the tile with an external 
data connection.  An earlier approach to the smart floor involved only one measur-
ing tile made of load cells, a steel plate, and data acquisition hardware, and was 
not intended to be hidden [52].  Rather, it was created as an alternative to bio-
metric identification by recognizing a person’s unique footstep profile.   
Two other approaches that utilize load cells and layered flooring to conceal the 
sensors are nearly identical to the first concept variant.  Liau et al. place a sensor 
in the center of every 60cm x 60cm wood covered tile [53], where Addlesee et al. 
place a sensor at each intersection of four carpet covered tiles [54].  Load cells are 
similar  in  principle  to  cantilever  beams  in  that  deflection  is  transduced  into  an 
electrical signal that can be interpreted.  Here, a literature review revealed that the 
first biologically-inspired concept is feasible and has been attempted.  
Investigating the second concept variant for smart flooring revealed only one 
existing design that is similar.  Researchers at Infineon Technologies have woven 
conductive fibers into carpet and attached them to tiny sensor modules inlaid into 
the fabric to build a mesh network [55].  The flooring can report where a person is 
located, which way they are moving and if a sensor module has failed.  Each con-
ductor in the design is a copper wire coated with silver to prevent corrosion and 
then  covered  with  polyester  [55].   A  German  textile  company,  Vorwerk,  has 
teamed  up  with  Infineon  to  develop  the  smart  carpet  [56,57].    The  Vor-
werk/Infineon product is similar in structure to the second concept variant created 
here in that a conductor is concealed and woven into a textile product.  Again, a 
literature review revealed that the biologically-inspired concept is feasible. 
This case study demonstrated that it is possible to systematically design using 
the search heuristics and take inspiration from biology in the process.  By analyz-
ing the biological system and making connections a designer can become inspired.  
 23 
It  is  through  these  correlations  that  the  designer  can  recognize  existing  designs 
that are similar or develop an innovative design. 
5.4.3 Chemical Sensor Case Study 
The systematic biologically-inspired design method presented here is able to in-
spire more than mechanical and electro-mechanical devices.  This case study pre-
sents the design of a chemical sensor following the approach closest to traditional 
systematic design (flow chart A of Figure 5.3).   
For this study, the needs and constraints of the chemical sensing device are de-
rived from the Handbook of Modern Sensors [58]: selectivity (only senses the de-
sired  chemical  in  the  presence  of  other  species),  quick  response  time,  reusable, 
and  utilizes  an  indirect  sensing  mechanism.    These  needs  and  constraints  are 
mapped to flows as shown in Table 5.6 to complete the first step of the methodol-
ogy.  Next, the black box model is created to guide the decomposition of the flows 
into a functional model.  Figure 5.10 provides the black box model.  Figure 5.11 
provides the conceptual functional model to complete step two of the methodolo-
gy.   
Table 5.6. Chemical Sensing Needs Mapped to Conceptual Flows.
 
 
Customer Need/Constraint
 
Functional Basis Flow
 
Selectivity
 
Status signal
 
Response time
 
Electrical energy
 
Reusable
 
Sensing layer (material)
 
Indirect sensing mechanism
 
Sensing layer (material)/Chemical stimulus (energy)
 
 
 
Fig. 5.10. Chemical Sensor Black Box Model.
 
 
The chemical sensing device black box and conceptual functional models show 
the generalized form of a chemical stimulus (i.e., chemical energy).  This allows 
the designer to query all possible forms of a chemical stimulus.  The device sub-
strate is also generalized as material to include all possible forms of material in the 
knowledge base.  Figure 5.11 demonstrates the indirect sensing mechanism with 
 24  
couple
 and 
change
, and the sensing element or transducer with 
detect
.  Electrical 
energy is utilized to power the sensor and transfer the detection status signal to the 
device capable of interpreting such signals, such as a computer.  The boundary of 
the conceptual functional model includes the sensing layer and powered sensing 
element.  
 
 
Fig. 5.11. Chemical Sensor Conceptual Functional Model.
 
 
Following step three, the Design Repository was queried for engineering and 
biological  entries.    The  components  for  each  function/flow  pair  returned  are 
shown in Table 5.7.  For ten of the 13 sensor functions the component list was 
short and easy to choose from.  The functions of 
change detect
, 
 and 
export signal
 
returned many possible components. 
Table 5.7. Design Repository Solutions Mapped to Function/Flow Pairs.
 
 
Function/Flow
 
Solutions from Design Repository
 
Import/ Material
 
Housing, reservoir, spring
 
Import/ Chemical Energy
 
Container, nozzle
 
Guide/ Chemical Energy
 
Tube
 
Couple/ Chemical Energy to Material Basket, container, iron, nozzle, carburetor, burner, housing
 
 
Import/ Electrical Energy
 
Battery, wire, circuit board, motor, cord, switch
 
Transmit/ Electrical Energy
 
Wire, battery contacts, circuit board, compound eye
 
Change/ Material
 
Blade, impeller, heating element, punch, filter, staple plate, 
popcorn popper
 
Detect/ Chemical Energy
 
Fly chemoreceptor, protein, animalia chemoreception, plantae 
chemoreception
 
Regulate/ Electrical Energy
 
Circuit board, actuator, heating element, switch, resistor, di-
ode
 
Convert/ Status to Control Signal
 
Circuit board
 
Export/ Chemical Energy
 
Nozzle, bowl, tube, exhaust, bucket
 
Export/ Electrical Energy
 
Wire, circuit board, cord, switch
 
Export/ Status Signal
 
LCD screen, circuit board, wire, cord, level, speaker
 
 25 
 
Considering the conceptual device as a whole and how one would use the de-
vice is an advantageous thought process for determining suitable components from 
a list.  With regards to changing the material as the first step in the indirect sensing 
mechanism the impeller, blade and punch require mechanical movement to change 
a material, whereas the staple plate, filter and heating element could change the 
chemical  stimulus  without  mechanical  movement.  The  conceptual  design  is  not 
fully determined at this point and could be influenced by the component(s) chosen 
from biological inspiration.  Therefore, the functions of 
change
 and 
detect
 will be 
considered together. 
Following step four of the methodology, connections need to be established to 
assist concept generation.   Bacteria employ the two component regulatory system 
for detection of extracellular signals and the signaling pathways consist of modu-
lar units called transmitters and receivers, both of which are proteins [59].  Fly an-
tennae  contain  chemically  sensitive  cells  (chemoreceptors)  hidden  deep  within 
pores, which allow the insect to experience olfaction (i.e., sense of smell) [60].  
The Animalia and Plantae mechanisms of chemoreception are not descriptive, and 
are meant to guide a designer in a direction of research.  Analysis of the biological 
components leads to the choice of fly chemoreceptor for the detect function block. 
Further  exploration  of  the  fly  antennae  reveals  that  the  insect  cuticle  (a  chitin-
protein outer cover) has elaborations in the form of trichoids (hairs), pegs, pegs in 
pits and flat surfaces, all of which provide multiple pores for chemicals to travel 
through [60].  Within the pore is a fluid-protein pathway to the dendritic (sensory) 
cell  membrane.    Once  the  chemical  molecule  reaches  the  fluid  surrounding  the 
dendrite membrane it bonds to an odorant binding protein and is carried to one of 
the receptor sites of the membrane [60].  When the two make contact in the cation 
concentrated fluid, a signal occurs as a voltage potential change across the mem-
brane, which is the signal to be transduced.  The sensing principles of fly antennae 
are complex and offer the designer inspirations for the function of detect, and, as 
expected, for the function of change [5].  
A filter is analogous to the porous cuticle, which would narrow down the selec-
tion of chemicals, or allow only one stimulus to interact with the sensing layer.  
The heating element is analogous to the odorant binding proteins and cell mem-
brane surface with receptor sites, in that, an electrified element is capable of at-
tracting polarized molecules (disregarding the heating aspect).  An impeller could 
be used to steer the desired chemical stimulus to the sensing element, which is 
analogous to the odorant binding proteins that shuttle stimuli to receptors.   
Biological inspiration considering morphology leads to a sensing element that 
has specifically shaped cavities or is uniformly porous, and is a good conductor.  
Any material that can be patterned by photolithography can achieve the desired 
surface.  Morphology of the fly antennae itself offers inspiration for a “stick-like” 
sensing element.  Another connection exists between the engineering component 
filter and permeable or ion-selective membranes, which are used in current sensor 
technology.  Therefore, permeable or ion-selective membranes are analogous to 
 26  
the porous cuticle.  Further analogies exist between the heating element and elec-
trical energy traveling through a conductor, which could be a copper wire, semi-
conductor, conducting polymer, etc.  Semiconductor electrodes that allow absorp-
tion  and  desorption  of  chemical  species  are  analogous  binding  and  removal  of 
odorants  from  the  cell  membrane  receptor  sites  within  the  fly  antennae,  which 
could also be used in the final concept. 
Performing step five, concept generation leads to two concept variants.  The 
first device supports a housing containing an electrified element (not for the pro-
duction of heat) acting as a barrier to the transducer that chemical energy is guided 
to from the container, or space.  The subsequent chemical energy is attracted to the 
electrified element and once bonding occurs, the electrical properties of the elec-
trified element change and generate a signal to be transduced as shown in Figure 
5.12.    The  electrical  property  change  of  the  electrified  element  fulfills  the  re-
quirement of an indirect sensing mechanism, which also supports reusability as the 
absorbed particles could be removed by heating the element.  An electronic circuit 
powers the transducer, decodes the sensor signal and produces an electrical signal 
analogous to the input.  The second device supports a housing containing a filter 
covering the sensing layer, which rests on the sensing element.  Only the chemical 
species that pass through the filter interact with the sensing element.  This interac-
tion generates a signal to be transduced as shown in Figure 5.13, but does not ful-
fill the requirement of an indirect sensing mechanism.  The chemical stimuli, alt-
hough filtered, still are allowed to interact with the detection layer.  An electronic 
circuit powers the transducer, decodes the sensor signal and produces an electrical 
signal analogous to the input.  Further material research is needed to accurately 
define the sensing layers for both concept variants. 
 
 
Fig. 5.12. Concept Variant One for Chemical Sensor. 
 27 
 
 
 
Fig. 5.13. Concept Variant Two for Chemical Sensor.
 
 
When researching if a sensor with an electrified element on a transducer exists, 
the first concept described above, conducting polymer sensors that are typically 
used for detection of gases was found.  The conducting polymer is deposited atop 
interdigital  electrodes,  which  make  it  the  dielectric  material  for  the  electrodes.  
When  a  gas  interacts  with  the  polymer  the  capacitance  between  the  electrodes 
changes and the output signal decreases [61,62].  These sensors are sometimes re-
ferred to as chemiresistors.  Functionally, a chemiresistor is identical to the first 
concept. 
The  second  concept  is  similar  to  an  ion-selective  electrode  (ISE)  or  ion-
selective  field  effect  transistor  (ISFET)  used  to  measure  pH.    An  ISE  has  high 
specificity to single charged ions and is made of a doped glass.  The glass allows 
only single charged ions, such as hydrogen, to pass through to an internal solution 
of neutral pH monitored by an electrode.  Concentration of hydrogen ions is corre-
lated  to  a  pH  value  by  taking  the  logarithm  of  the  concentration  [63,64].    An 
ISFET  is  the  microelectronic  version  of  an  ISE  and  is  similar  in  structure  to  a 
MOSFET [63-65].  Instead of glass, the membrane is made as a thin film over an 
insulation  layer  of  metal  oxide  or  nitrate  on  a  p-doped  substrate.    Two  n-type 
doped regions are added to the substrate for connection of the source and drain, 
while the gate is connected to the sensing layer beneath the membrane.  Here the 
sensing layer is a liquid or insulation material and the sensing element is an elec-
trode.  Functionally, an ISE is identical to the second concept. 
This case study demonstrated that it is possible to systematically design a sen-
sor and take inspiration from biology in the process.  By analyzing the biological 
system and making connections a designer can become inspired.  It is through the-
 28  
se correlations that the designer can recognize existing designs that are similar or 
develop an innovative design.   
5.4.4 Heat Exchanger Case Study 
This case study presents the design of a heat exchanging component for use in fu-
ture hydrogen vehicles following the approach of a known process before query-
ing is performed.  Needs for the heat exchanger design are set by an external re-
search group that wanted to explore biologically-inspired concepts for distributing 
hydrogen on the micro scale.  The external group had exhausted all their avenues 
and expressed a need for more ideas, which satisfies step one of the methodology.  
Through discussion a common understanding of distributing hydrogen on the mi-
cro  scale  and  the  role  heat  exchange  would  play  in  that  process  was  reached.  
From here the black box model, as shown in Figure 5.14, was created.  A known 
biological process that distributes material is circulation of blood by the vascular 
system  of  the  human  body.    This  is  a  known  biological  process  that  is  used  to 
begin  the  biologically-inspired  design  process.    When  querying  the  biological 
knowledge base for circulation many results lead to descriptions of the heart, but 
also  mention  gas  exchange  organs.    This  preliminary  search  did  not  result  in  a 
wide variety of inspiring biological systems.  Therefore, to widen the inspiration 
space the biological terms that correspond to the engineering function of 
distribute
 
were retrieved from the engineering-to-biology thesaurus.   
 
 
Fig. 5.14. Black Box Model of a Heat Exchanger. 
 
In  the  engineering-to-biology  thesaurus  the  following  seven  biological  terms 
correspond to the engineering term of distribute:  circulate, diffusion, exchange, 
disperse, scatter, spread, spray.  Circulate resulted in a narrow set of results.  The 
list does reveal that the term 
exchange
 is used in biological literature.  With a new 
keyword chosen, step three of the methodology can be performed.  The biological 
knowledge base was queried to identify biological systems that perform the func-
tion of 
exchange
.  The resulting query results from [50] are: 
1. skin 
 
 29 
2. gas exchange surfaces of animals 
 
3. fish gills 
 
4. lungs of a bird 
 
5. respiratory system of insects 
 
6. countercurrent heat exchanger in fish 
 
7. stomata 
 
8. abscisic acid 
 
It is important to note that the listed results are not the only results provided by 
the  query.    These  eight  were  the  most  interesting  and  provided  the  most  infor-
mation for biological inspiration.  Plants, fish, birds, mammals and insects all offer 
inspiration  for  this  case  study.    Notice  that  not  all  the  biological  solutions  deal 
with gas exchange.  Exploring other implementations of exchange increases the 
design space and creative solution potential.   
As this design is for another research group, a meeting was held to discuss the 
biological systems that were identified to choose a biological system for further 
investigation as well as work through the remaining steps of the methodology.  A 
connection  established  during  the  meeting  is  the  similarity  of  engineering  mass 
transfer concepts and the diffusion of respiratory gases into an insect.  Although a 
direct  relationship  between  the  domains  was  recognized,  the  external  research 
group did not see value in pursuing the relationship further.  While reviewing a 
detailed description of the avian respiratory system the discussion led to a connec-
tion that revealed the solution of a competing research group in the area of heat 
exchangers for hydrogen vehicles.  During the first inhale/exhale cycle of a bird, 
air travels to the trachea and into posterior air sacs, and then is moved to the para-
bronchi  area  where  the  exchange  takes  place  [31].    During  the  second  in-
hale/exhale cycle the air moves forward to the cranial air sacs and then exits the 
bird [30].  Realizing that the air within a bird’s lungs essentially travels in a circle 
sparked discussion of a spiral shaped surface that would effectively distribute hy-
drogen.  That is, in fact, what a competing research group did [66]. 
While reviewing a detailed description of gills along with Figure 5.15, howev-
er, a researcher immediately made a connection between the gills of fish and hy-
drogen distribution.  Considering the fish blood as the coolant and the water sur-
rounding the fish as hydrogen, a distribution scheme inspired by the morphology 
and physiology of fish gills was discussed.  The concept sketch is shown in Figure 
5.16.  In this case, the biological functional model was not required, nor the engi-
neering  knowledge  base  query.    The  concept  generation  step  began  during  the 
meeting, and the final concept was finalized by the external research group.   
 30  
 
Fig. 5.15. Fish Gills [67]. 
 
 
 
Fig. 5.16. Concept Sketch for Heat Exchanger.
 
 
This case study demonstrated that it is possible to systematically design for a 
portion of a larger problem with only a small amount of information as well as 
take inspiration from biology in the process.  By analyzing the biological system 
and making connections a designer can become inspired.  It is through these corre-
lations that the designer can recognize existing designs that are similar or develop 
an innovative design. 
5.5 Summary 
The design methodology presented here represents a specific design approach de-
voted to developing biologically-inspired solutions.  It challenges and guides a de-
signer to make connections between the engineering and biology domains to facil-
itate  innovative  design.    It  takes  an  organic  approach  to  systematic  design  by 
providing a designer many avenues that lead to an inspired design.  It also is envi-
sioned as an inventive and iterative process, in terms of developing connections 
 31 
between systems at multiple levels of fidelity.  As one level, or scale, of the bio-
logical system becomes understood it leads to a deeper understanding and a great-
er curiosity to explore further.  Thus, leading to multiple innovative designs.  The 
preceding four chapters presented the individual parts of the framework.  They co-
alesce in the systematic biologically-inspired design method as demonstrated by 
the smart flooring, chemical sensor and heat exchanger cases studies.  Validation 
of the design methodology was proven through matching each of the generated 
concepts in the case studies with existing solutions or technologies.  It was shown 
how the connections made between biological systems and engineered were key to 
arriving at the biologically-inspired inspired designs.
 
5.6 References 
1.
 
McKean  E  (2005)  The  new  Oxford  American  dictionary.  Oxford  University  Press,  New 
York 
2.
 
Nagel  JKS,  Stone  RB,  McAdams  DA  (2010)  Function-Based  Biology  Inspired  Concept 
Generation. In:  Biomimetics, Learning From Nature. In-Tech, Croatia,  
3.
 
Nagel JKS, Stone RB, McAdams DA An Engineering-to-Biology Thesaurus for Engineer-
ing Design. In: ASME IDETC/CIE 2010 DTM-28233, Montreal, Quebec, Canada., 2010.  
4.
 
Nagel  JKS,  Nagel  RL,  Stone  RB,  McAdams  DA  (2010)  Function-Based  Biologically-
Inspired Concept Generation. Artificial Intelligence for Engineering Design, Analysis and 
Manufacturing 24 (4):521-535 
5.
 
Nagel JKS, Stone RB, McAdams DA Exploring the Use of Category and Scale to Scope a 
Biological Functional Model. In: ASME IDETC/CIE 2010, DTM-28873, Montreal, Que-
bec, Canada, 2010.  
6.
 
Nagel JKS, Stone RB (2012) A Computational Approach to Biologically-inspired Design. 
Artificial Intelligence for Engineering Design, Analysis and Manufacturing, special issue 
DCC 2010 26 (2):161-176 
7.
 
Pahl G, Beitz W, Feldhusen J, Grote KH (2007) Engineering Design: A Systematic Ap-
proach. 3rd edn. Springer Verlag, 
8.
 
Nagel JKS, Stone RB (2011) A Systematic Approach to Biologically-inspired Engineering 
Design. Paper presented at the ASME IDETC/CIE 2011, DTM-47398, Washington, D.C., 
USA 
9.
 
Biomimicry 
Institute 
(2010) 
Biomimicry: 
A 
Tool 
for 
Innovation. 
http://www.biomimicryinstitute.org/about-us/biomimicry-a-tool-for-innovation.html.  
10. Helms M, Vattam SS, Goel AK (2009) Biologically Inspired Design: Products and Process-
 
es. Design Studies 30 (5):606-622 
11. Casakin H (2006) Visual Analogy as a Cognitive Strategy in the Design Process: Expert 
 
Versus 
Novice 
Performance. 
Journal 
of 
Design 
Research 
4 
(2):DOI: 
10.1504/JDR.2004.009846 
12. Gentner D (1988) Analogical Inference and Access, vol Analogica. Lecture Notes in Artifi-
 
cial Intelligence. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, Los Altos, CA 
13. Gentner  D  (1983)  Structure-Mapping:  A  Theoretical  Framework  for  Analogy.  Cognitive 
 
Science 7:155-170 
14. Gick M, Holyoak K (1980) Analogical problem-solving. Cognitive Psychology 12:306-355 
 
15. Goel A (1997) Design, analogy and creativity. IEEE Expert Intelligent Systems and Their 
 
Applications 12 (3):62-70 
 32  
16. Hofstadter DR (1995) Fluid concepts & creative analogies : computer models of the fun-
 
damental mechanisms of thought. Basic Books, New York 
17. Tsujimoto K, Miura S, Tsumaya A, Nagai Y, Chakrabarti A, Taura T A Method for Crea-
 
tive  Behavioral  Design  Based  on  Analogy  and  Blending  from  Natural  Things.  In:  2008 
ASME IDETC/CIE, New York, USA, 2008. DETC2008-49389,  
18. Linsey J, Wood K, Markman A (2008) Modality and Representation in Analogy. AIEDAM 
 
22 (2):85-100 
19. Balazs ME, Brown DC (2001) Design Simplification by Analogical Reasoning. In: Rizzi, 
 
Cugini,  Wozny  (eds)  Knowledge  Intensive  Computer  Aided  Design.  Kluwer  Academic 
Publishers,  
20. Mak TW, Shu LH (2004) Abstraction of Biological Analogies for Design. CIRP Annals 
 
531 (1):117-120 
21. Bhatta SR, Goel AK (1997) An analogical theory of creativity in design. In:  Case Based 
 
Reasoning Research and Development, vol 1266. Berlin/Heidelberg, pp 565-574 
22. Smith GF (1998) Idea generation techniques: a formulary of active ingredients. Journal of 
 
Creative Behavior 32 (2):107–133 
23. Nagai Y, Taura T Formal Description of Concept-Synthesizing Process for Creative De-
 
sign. In: Gero JS (ed) Design Computing and Cognition’06, Dordrecht, 2006. Springer, pp 
443-460 
24. Johnson-Laird P (1989) Analogy and the exercise of creativity. In: Vosniadou S, Ortony A 
 
(eds) Similarity and analogical reasoning. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, pp 313-
331 
25. Fan Z, Chen J, Zou J, Bullen D, Liu C, Delcomyn F (2002) Design and Fabrication of Arti-
 
ficial Lateral Line Flow Sensors. Journal of Micromechanics and Microengineering 12:655-
661 
26. Motamed M, Yan J (2005) A Review of Biological, Biomimetic and Miniature Force Sens-
 
ing for Microflight. Paper presented at the IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelli-
gent Robots and Systems (IROS),  
27. Gnatzy W, Grunert U, Bender M (1987) Campaniform sensilla of Calliphora 
 
vicina 
(Insec-
ta, Diptera) I. Topography. Zoomorphology 160:312-319 
28. Grunert U, Gnatzy W (1987) Campaniform sensilla of Calliphora 
 
vicina 
(Insecta, Diptera) 
II. Typology. Zoomorphology 106 (320-328) 
29. Wicaksono DHB, Pandraud G, Craciun G, Vincent JFV, French PJ Fabrication and Initial 
 
Cahracterisation Results of a Micromachined Biomimetic Strain Sensor Inspired from the 
Campaniform Sensillum of Insects. In: IEEE Sensors 2004, 2004. pp 542-545 
30. Vattam S, Helms M, Goel A Compound Analogical Design: Interaction Between Problem 
 
Decomposition and Analogical Transfer in Biologically Inspired Design. In: Third Interna-
tional Conference on Design Computing and Cognition, Atlanta, 2008. Berlin:Springer, pp 
377-396 
31. Campbell NA, Reece JB (2003) Biology. Pearson Benjamin Cummings, San Francisco 
 
32. Shu LH, Hansen HN, Gegeckaite A, Moon J, Chan C (2006) Case Study in Biomimetic De-
 
sign:    Handling  and  Assembly  of  Microparts.  Paper  presented  at  the  ASME  2006 
IDETC/CIE, Philadelphia, PA,  
33. Hubka V, Eder EW (1984) Theory of Technical Systems. Springer-Verlag, Berlin 
 
34. Lindemann U, Gramann J Engineering Design Using Biological Principles. In: International 
 
Design Conference - DESIGN 2004, Dubrovnik, 2004.  
35. Otto KN, Wood KL (2001) Product Design: Techniques in Reverse Engineering and New 
 
Product Development. Prentice-Hall, Upper Saddle River, New Jersey 
36. Vincent JFV, Mann DL (2002) Systematic technology transfer from biology to engineering. 
 
Philosophical Transactions of the The Royal Society London A 360:159-173 
37. Casakin H (2007) Metaphors in Design Problem Solving: Implications for Creativity. Inter-
 
national Journal of Design 1 (2):21-33 
 33 
38. Casakin H (2006) Assessing the use of metaphors in the design process. Environment and 
 
Planning B: Planning and Design 33 (2):253-268 
39. Hey J, Linsey J, Agogino AM, Wood KL (2008) Analogies and Metaphors in Creative De-
 
sign. International Journal of Engineering Education 24 (2):283-294 
40. Forty A (1989) Of Cars, Clothes and Carpets: Design Metaphors in Architectural Thought. 
 
Journal of Design History 2 (1):1-14. doi:doi:10.1093/jdh/2.1.1 
41. Dollens  D  (2009)  BioDigital  Architecture  Uses  Metaphor  to  Design  Living  Systems. 
 
http://sensingarchitecture.com/3832/biodigital-architecture-uses-metaphor-to-design-living-
systems-dennis-dollens-video/.  
42. Ullman DG (2009) The Mechanical Design Process 4th Edition. McGraw-Hill, Inc., New 
 
York 
43. Ulrich KT, Eppinger SD (2004) Product design and development. McGraw-Hill/Irwin, Bos-
 
ton 
44. Voland G (2004) Engineering By Design. 2nd edn. Pearson Prentice Hall, Upper Saddle 
 
River, NJ 
45. Hyman B (1998) Engineering design. Prentice-Hall, New Jersey 
 
46. Dym CL, Little P (2004) Engineering design : a project-based introduction. John Wiley, 
 
New York 
47. Stone  RB  (1997)  Towards  a  Theory  of  Modular  Design.  University  of  Texas  at  Austin, 
 
Austin, TX 
48. Stone R, Wood K (2000) Development of a Functional Basis for Design. Journal of Me-
 
chanical Design 122 (4):359-370 
49. Nagel JK (2010) Systematic Design of Biologically-Inspired Engineering Solutions. Doc-
 
toral Dissertation, Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR 
50. Purves WK, Sadava D, Orians GH, Heller HC (2001) Life, The Science of Biology. 6 edn. 
 
Sinauer Associates, Sunderland, MA 
51. Richardson B, Leydon K, Fernström M, Paradiso JA (2004) Z-Tiles: Building Blocks for 
 
Modular, Pressure-Sensing Floorspaces. Paper presented at the Conference on Human Fac-
tors In Computing Systems (CHI), Vienna, Austria,  
52. Orr RJ, Abowd GD (2000) The Smart Floor: A Mechanism for Natural User Identification 
 
and Tracking. Paper presented at the Conference on Human Factors In Computing Systems 
(CHI), Hague, Netherlands,  
53. Liau W-H, Wu C-L, Fu L-C (2008) Inhabitants Tracking System in a Cluttered Home Envi-
 
ronment Via Floor Load Sensors. IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineer-
ing 5 (1):10-20 
54. Addlesee MD, Jones A, Livesey F, Samaria F (1997) The ORL active floor. IEEE Personal 
 
Communication 4 (5):35–41 
55. IEE-Institution of Electrical Engineers (2003) Research news - Walk this way for the smart 
 
floor. Electronics Systems and Software, vol 1.  
56. Vorwerk  &  Co.  TGCK  (2004)  Infineon  Thinking  Carpet.  http://www.vorwerk-
 
carpet.com/sc/vorwerk/bildmeldung_thinkCarpet_en.html.  
57. Crane D (2005) New High-Tech Sensor-Laiden Smart Carpet May Revolutionize Building 
 
Security. 
http://www.defensereview.com/new-high-tech-sensor-laiden-smart-carpet-may-
revolutionize-building-security/.  
58. Fraden J (2004) Handbook of modern sensors : physics, designs, and applications. Springer, 
 
New York 
59. Stock AM, Robinson VL, Goudreau PN (2000) Two-component signal transduction. Annu-
 
al Review of Biochemistry 69:183-215 
60. Mitchell BK (2003) Chemoreception. In:  Encyclopedia of insects. Academic Press, Am-
 
sterdam; Boston, pp 169-174 
61. György I (2008) Conducting Polymers: A New Era in Electrochemistry. Springer-Verlag, 
 
Berlin 
62. Bai H, Shi G (2007) Gas Sensors Based on Conducting Polymers. Sensors 7:267-307 
 
 34  
63. Grundler P (2007) Chemical sensors an introduction for scientists and engineers. Springer, 
 
Berlin; London 
64. Eggins BR (2002) Chemical sensors and biosensors. Analytical techniques in the sciences. 
 
J. Wiley, Chichester; Hoboken, NJ 
65. Liao H-K, Yang E-S, Chou J-C, Chung W-Y, Sun T-P, Hsiung S-K (1999) Temperature 
 
and optical characteristics of tin oxide membrane gate ISFET. IEEE Transactions on Elec-
tron Devices 46 (12):2278–2281 
66. Venere  E  (2010)  Engineers  design,  build  major  component  for  hydrogen  cars. 
 
http://www.physorg.com/news186221598.html.  
67. Raven PH, Johnson GB (2002) Biology. McGraw-Hill, Boston 
 
 
 
View publication stats
View publication stats
